Don't be filming my passwords.
不要拍到我的密碼
I used to have a shirt in high school
我在高中的時候有一件T恤
that said "technology must be used to liberate the individual."
上面說 "科技將使每個人獲得自由"
And I didn't really know what it meant for years,
其實好多年以來 我都不知道那是什麼意思,
'cause I didn't really think about it.
因為我其實沒有仔細思考這個事情.
But today I look back and I'm like, "oh man, hell yeah, I like that shirt."
但是如今我回想起來, 其實我還蠻喜歡那件衣服的
I'm glad I wore that shirt, 'cause it's how I really feel today.
我還蠻開心我有那件T恤的 因為那就是我目前的感覺
My name is Daniel Mross.
我的名字是Daniel mross.
Today is may 3rd, 2012.
今天是2012年5月3日
I go through college and watch the Internet come
我讀大學的時候看到了網路的發展
and all these different things. And now, like, Bitcoin,
還有其他許多的進步 那現在還有了比特幣
it's just a single technology built on top of the Internet,
他其實只是一個架構在網際網路上的技術,
but it's so fascinating because there's so many
但卻是如此令人著迷 因為你可以透過他
freaking things you can do with it.
做出很多特別的事情
It's also just a big experiment.
而且他就像一個大型實驗.
There's no guarantees with it.
但沒有任何人知道會發生什麼事 .
We might just all be wasting our time...
我們也可能就是浪費了時間...
Exploring concepts and ideas.
去探索他的原理與一些想法.
It's at this crossroads of technology
目前我們就在一個科技
and philosophy and politics and everything.
與哲學、政治還有很多東西的交會點上
Just be a part of it. It's fun.
成為其中的一員吧. 還蠻好玩的.
It's crazy though, but it's fun.
聽起來蠻瘋狂的, 但就是好玩.
Um, first question is
恩，第一個問題是
what is Bitcoin?
什麼是比特幣?
I can't tell you what Bitcoin is
我沒辦法直接用幾句話告訴你
in just a few sentences.
什麼是比特幣
It takes time to understand it,
我們需要花一點時間去了解他,
the same way it took people time to understand
其實就跟當初在1994年
what the Internet was
我們需要時間去理解
back in 1994.
什麼是Internet一樣
That little Mark with the "a" and then the ring around it.
那個符號有個a 然後外面有一個圈
- "At"? - See, that's what I said.
- "@"? - 對，就是我說的
- Mm-hmm. - Katie said she thought it was "about."
- 嗯. - Katie 說那是"關於"的符號.
-  Yeah. - Elizabeth Vargas: Oh, Internet is...
-  沒錯. -  那Internet是...
- - That massive computer network... -  Right.
-  大型的電腦網路 沒錯.
...the one that's becoming really big now.
...而且變得越來越大.
Allison, can you explain what Internet is?
Allison, 你可以解釋什麼是Internet嗎？
When the Internet was taking off,
當Internet開始發展時,
I was in college at Virginia tech
我在維吉尼亞的一所大學
studying computer science.
就讀電腦科學.
Looking back, it's amazing to think about
現在想起來, 整個網路的變遷
how much the world was changing.
跟他對世界的影響 真的太不可思議了.
Hey, Dan, ready for the game?
嗨, Dan, 要出去比賽了嗎?
I'm just finishing up here with my new kayaking friends.
我在跟幾個朋友比賽划船 就快結束了
Kayaking friends on your computer?
跟朋友划船? 在電腦上?
Yeah, I just got America online.
對啊,我最近才剛裝了"美國線上"
That same type of innovation is happening again
就像這樣的創新突破 正在透過
with Bitcoin.
比特幣重新發生
It's the smartest people in the room
一群聰明的人在房間內
that are the most excited about this. So what are they seeing?
他們對此非常的興奮 所以他們看到了什麼?
The Internet changed the way the world communicates
Internet改變了世界溝通的方式
Bitcoin changes the way money works.
比特幣則改變了金錢運作的方式.
You can basically put a bank in your pocket.
你的口袋幾乎就是一間銀行.
Psst!
噓!
Wanna buy some secret stuff?
要買一些秘方嗎?
There is now a new note
現在人們逐漸在開始
that people are starting to talk about--
討論一種新貨幣
The Bitcoin.
比特幣
The money of the future.
一種未來的貨幣
Bitcoin was created to provide
比特幣的設計目的
an alternative to the banking system.
就是為了取代 目前的銀行金融系統
We're in the midst
我們正在面臨
of a serious financial crisis
一個嚴重的經濟災難
and the federal government is responding
而聯邦政府正在積極的
with decisive action.
採取各種應變措施
Unlike most currencies,
不同於一般的貨幣,
Bitcoins are issued according to a set of fixed rules.
比特幣是透過固定的規則發行.
The idea was to create money whose value
如此設計的目的 就是為了避免
couldn't be manipulated by a central authority.
比特幣的價值 受到一個中央機構控制.
The government, no matter how many guns they draw,
一個政府組織 無論他有多少的武力
cannot change a mathematical problem.
都沒有辦法改變 一個數學架構
They can point their guns at "two plus two,"
他們可以想辦法用武力去改變 "2+2"
but it's always gonna equal four.
但是永遠都會等於4.
It's fascinating to imagine
一個全球的分散式貨幣系統
what it means to have global decentralized money.
是一件聽起來 讓人如此著迷的事情.
And that's what's happening.
而且現在就在發生.
My five-year-old's birthday.
我五歲小朋友的生日
First round of burgers is ready.
第一輪的漢堡肉好了
Second round is going on in a second.
第二輪馬上就來
First round of burgers is ready!
第一輪的漢堡肉來了!
First round.
第一輪.
Eliza Mross: Dan has always been an idea guy.
Dan是一個時常充滿想法的人.
Bitcoin is the perfect combination
比特幣剛好完美的結合了
of how can I change the world and make it better,
我如何讓世界變得更好,
but how can I also be a nerd?
而且又符合怪才的個性?
So mostly I've just been supporting him
雖然看似瘋狂
in this craziness.
但是我都支持他.
Eliza and I met in college,
Eliza跟我在大學認識,
and we've been married for seven years.
而我們已經結婚七年了.
We live in Pittsburgh, where I'm from,
我們住在Pittsburgh, 也是我長大的地方
and we have three boys,
我們有三個小男生,
I've spent most of my career
我大部分的職業是
as a database administrator.
一位資料庫管理員.
But for the past two years, I've been consumed with Bitcoin.
但是在過去的兩年 我都把時間耗在比特幣上.
Bitcoins come into existence through a process called mining.
比特幣透過"挖礦"的方式來發行.
I build computers to mine for Bitcoins.
我架設了一堆電腦來"挖礦".
I'm glad that it's finally getting a little bit cooler out.
好在外面終於沒那麼熱了
My wife won't be as angry that the basement is so hot.
那我太太就不會對於地下室太熱 而有點生氣
I've still got a bunch of mining rigs running right now.
現在我還有一堆礦機正在運作
Actually they're right down here, if you wanna go take a look.
如果你想要看一下的話 其實他們就在裡面
Here they are.
就在這裡
So what is Bitcoin?
什麼是比特幣?
Bitcoin is a revolutionary technology
比特幣 是一套創新的科技
that enables a new way to send payments over the Internet.
是一種透過網路 來進行支付的方式.
- - You can think of it as an open accounting system
-  你可以想像成 是一種"公眾會計系統"
where thousands of computers all over the world
全世界數以千計的電腦一起運作
work together to track ownership of digital tokens called Bitcoins.
然後來確認"比特幣"的個別擁有權
When you send someone Bitcoins,
當你用比特幣付款給某人時,
the transaction is broadcast to the entire network.
這筆交易會廣播到整個網路.
After it's verified,
當交易被確認後,
it's recorded in a public ledger
這筆交易會被記錄到一個
called the blockchain.
叫做blockchain(區塊鍊)的公共帳本
The blockchain contains a record
blockchain記錄了
of every Bitcoin transaction that has occurred
自從比特幣系統誕生以來
since the system began,
的每一筆交易記錄
and it's shared and maintained on the network,
而且他是被整個網路所共享, 並持續更新
so everyone keeps the books, so to speak.
所以每個人都有完整的一套資料.
Most currencies are issued by a central authority
目前大部分的貨幣 都是透過一個"中央機構"所發行
that controls the money supply.
這個機構控制了金錢的供給
Bitcoin is a peer-to-peer system,
比特幣是一個點對點系統,
so there is no central authority.
所以並沒有一個"中央機構".
Instead Bitcoins are issued to users
反而 比特幣是透過
who help process transactions in the network.
那些維持網路運作的人所發行
This is known as Bitcoin mining.
這個過程就叫做"挖礦".
Bitcoin miners are specialized computers
比特幣的"礦機"是一種特殊的電腦程式
that do the work required to verify
主要工作 就是確認比特幣的交易資料
and record transactions in the blockchain.
並將這些資料 記錄在blockchain中.
As a reward for their work,
那他們工作的獎勵,
the miners earn Bitcoins,
就是比特幣,
and this is how new Bitcoins are released into circulation.
這就是比特幣如何產生 並進入現金流的過程.
The system is programmed
這套系統透過程式控制
so that only 21 million Bitcoins will ever exist.
所以總共只會發行 兩千一百萬個比特幣.
And as time goes by,
隨著時間過去,
the mining reward decreases.
"挖礦"的獎勵將會降低.
The result is a predictable supply
這樣的結果就是 可以預期的比特幣的發行總數
that's governed by scarcity,
而這是依據整個網路的規模而計算,
making Bitcoins somewhat like a digital gold.
製造比特幣的過程 有點類似於開採數位金礦.
It's the first currency of the Internet.
他是第一個屬於Internet的貨幣.
And everyone is free to use it.
而且每個人都可以免費的使用.
With Bitcoin, you can send any amount of money
藉由比特幣 你可以傳送任何大小的金額
to anyone anywhere in the world
給世界上的任何一個人
as easily as sending an email.
就跟寄E-Mail一樣簡單.
My brother Nick is a filmmaker.
我的兄弟Nick 是一位影片工作者.
After hearing me talk about Bitcoin incessantly for months,
在聽我說完 最近比特幣幾個月的漲幅之後
we decided to start documenting things.
我們決定 來用影片記錄一些事情.
Hey, I don't think we'll need the small camera.
嘿 我覺得我們用不到小攝影機.
- It can't hurt. -  No, I'd rather just leave it behind.
- 又沒關係. 不,我覺得還是把他留下來.
I have so much equipment. Do you mind?
我有很多設備 你會介意嗎?
Damn, you really cramped it up, huh?
你是玩真的囉?對吧?
Not that bad. What do you mean?
沒那麼糟糕啦 你是指什麼?
- Jeez. - Dude, they're right there.
- 哇. - 老兄,就在那邊啊.
Right in the back. Right there.
就在後面啦. 在那邊.
I was convinced that Bitcoin was going to be huge,
我相信比特幣將會蓬勃發展,
and I knew there were a lot of others like me out there.
而且我知道有不少人 跟我相信一樣的事情.
Zipped my keys in my pocket, so I don't forget 'em later.
把鑰匙用拉鍊固定在口袋裡, 那這樣我就不會忘了.
Bitcoin was created by what's believed to be a pseudonym,
比特幣的創造者, 是一個叫做satoshi nakamoto（中本聰）的人
a guy named Satoshi Nakamoto.
我們認為這個名字應該只是一個化名
Invented in '09 by a fictitious person
在2009年被一個叫做satoshi nakamoto
named Satoshi Nakamoto...
的人所發明的...
On Halloween 2008,
在2008年的萬聖節,
someone using the name Satoshi Nakamoto.
某個人用了 satoshi nakamoto的名字.
Posted on a cryptography mailing list...
在一個討論加密的郵件群組裡面 張貼了一篇文章...
The post contained a link to a white paper
這篇文章連結到一份 技術白皮書
in which Satoshi proposed a new type of payment system for the Internet.
satoshi 提出了一個 建構於網路之上的新支付系統.
It described a protocol that used peer-to-peer networking,
裡面說明了一種點對點協定,
proof of work and public key cryptography.
工作成果認證 以及公鑰加密技術.
For years, computer scientists had been experimenting
數年來，技術學者們 都想要運用這些技術
with these technologies to create digital money.
創造一個虛擬貨幣系統.
But Satoshi discovered a way to combine them
而satoshi找到一種
that had never been done before.
創新的方式結合他們.
In doing so, he invented Bitcoin.
如此一來, 他發明了比特幣.
There are no records of Nakamoto's existence
在比特幣被發明之前
prior to the creation of Bitcoin.
從來沒有nakamoto的存在記錄.
On his profile page,
在他的個人頁面中,
he claimed to be a 34-year-old man
他聲稱他是一位34歲
living in Japan.
住在日本的男人.
Although Satoshi Nakamoto is a Japanese name,
雖然satoshi是一個日本名字,
he wrote in perfect English when communicating online
他在網路上使用流暢的英文書寫能力
and went through great lengths to keep his identity unknown.
而且他花了很大的功夫 隱藏自己的身份.
Nonetheless, programmers and cryptographers
不過, 全世界的加密學者
all across the world recognized the brilliance of Satoshi's design.
與工程師們 都一致認可satoshi的驚妙傑作.
And began collaborating with him to further develop Bitcoin.
而且也開始跟他合作 共同參與比特幣的開發.
In October of 2009,
2009年10月,
the first exchange rate was published.
出現首次的兌換匯率.
Listing the value of 1,309 Bitcoins at $1.
兌換匯率為 1美金兌換1309個比特幣
Bitcoins were cheap, and through the following year,
比特幣那幾年間的價值都很便宜
they continued to trade for fractions of a cent.
其價值一直在幾毛錢徘徊.
In the spring of 2010,
2010年的春天,
a Florida man named Laszlo
一位住在佛羅里達的Laszlo
decided to try using his Bitcoins to purchase something.
想嘗試用比特幣買些東西
He offered 10,000 Bitcoins
他說他將會支付一萬個比特幣
to anyone who would buy him pizza.
給可以賣披薩給他的人.
A man in London accepted
有一個住在倫敦的人同意了
and placed a long-distance phone call,
而且也打了一通越洋電話,
ordering him two pizzas from papa John's.
幫他從papa John's 訂購了兩片披薩.
This is generally acknowledged
這是目前公認世界上第一個
as the first Bitcoin transaction for a tangible good.
透過比特幣交易實際貨物的紀錄.
Bitcoin was gaining momentum,
比特幣正在蓄勢待發,
but in order for it to thrive
但是要讓他茁壯成長
the coins needed to be more widely accessible.
比特幣需要被容易取得.
A Tokyo-based exchange named Mt. Gox was
位在日本的交易所 mt. Gox
the first on the scene to take hold of the Marketplace
是第一個專門交易比特幣的市場
and trading volume started to pick up.
而他的價值也不斷提高.
By November 2010,
到2010年11月,
already 4 million Bitcoins had been mined.
已經有超過四百萬個比特幣 被"開採".
And the exchange price briefly spiked to 50¢ per coin.
而匯率則提高到50美分.
The Market awoke and Bitcoin was starting to look like
這時,比特幣交易市場 開始發現了
it might have real potential as a currency.
他將可成為替代貨幣的潛力.
His name is Julian Assange.
他叫做Julian Assange.
Assange and his colleagues
Assange跟他的同事們
collect confidential information and then make it public.
蒐集各種機密資料 並予以公開.
The release of 250,000 state department documents
250,000機密國防資料的外洩
no doubt presents a serious dilemma for this country.
無疑造成了這個國家的兩難.
Following a massive release
後來因為揭露了大量的
of secret U.S. diplomatic cables,
機密外交電報內文,
donations to Wikileaks were blocked
所有可以捐款至 維基解密的管道都被封鎖
by Bank of America, Visa, Mastercard,
包含美國銀行, visa, 萬事達卡,
PayPal and Western union.
PayPal 以及西聯匯款.
An article in "PC World" suggested that Bitcoin
這時"pc world"的一篇文章
could be used as a workaround
建議比特幣會是一種
to send donations to Wikileaks.
可以讓維基解密收到捐款的方式.
One of Satoshi's last known posts
這時 satoshi發表了最後的貼文
was in response to the article and stated...
回應這篇文章...
Shortly after that
在那之後
Satoshi disappeared from the forums
satoshi 從論壇消失
and was never heard from again.
再也沒人得到他的音訊.
Two months later the silk road anonymous Marketplace was launched.
兩個月後 一個匿名線上市場"絲綢之路"上線.
It functioned as an online black Market
基本是一個線上黑市
for drugs and other illicit goods
從藥物到各種非法商品均有出售
and used Bitcoin exclusively,
他的貨幣使用比特幣,
because it made the money trail
因為你幾乎無法追蹤
nearly impossible to trace.
比特幣的金錢流向.
The silk road caught the attention
"絲綢之路"受到了公眾矚目
of New York senator Charles Schumer
紐約參議員Charles schumer
who was outraged and publicly called
在了解之後非常氣憤 並要求
for a crackdown on the site.
要關閉這個網站.
Heroin, opium, cannabis, ecstasy,
海洛因,鴉片,煙草,快樂丸
psychedelics, stimulants.
- 迷幻藥, 興奮劑.
It's unbelievable.
真是太誇張了.
Throughout all this,
與此同時,
the exchange price continued to climb.
比特幣的匯率持續攀升.
By February of 2011,
到2011年2月,
Bitcoin reached parity with the U.S. dollar.
比特幣的匯率與美金同價.
Sparking an influx of new users and speculators.
引進了更多的使用者與投機者.
By June the price had soared to a peak of $31
到6月，匯率攀升到31美元
before it came crashing down.
這時發生一場災難.
As the Market tanked, the Mt. Gox exchange was hacked,
就在瘋狂下跌的同時, mt. Gox交易所被入侵,
further shaking the confidence of investors
進一步的侵蝕了投資者的自信
and hammering the price all the way down
並持續的讓匯率下滑
to the $2 range by October.
到了10月的2美元.
While Bitcoin enthusiasts kept hope,
比特幣愛好者依然保持樂觀,
skeptics were quick to share their hindsights
而懷疑者則大肆宣傳他們的論點
and rants on blogs and in news articles.
從部落格到新聞媒體.
Many thought that the party was over
大家都認為比特幣玩完了
and that Bitcoin was on its way out.
比特幣也到了退場的時候.
I went online and I bought one Bitcoin last night.
我昨天到網路上買了一個比特幣.
Really? It's the future.
真的?那可是未來趨勢呢.
I don't know.
我不知道.
It didn't feel real.
感覺不太像真的.
No. Real's gonna change.
你錯了,現實將會改變.
Just watch.
就等著看好了.
Today I sent a total of...
今天我傳送了約...
2700 Bitcoins
2700個比特幣
to butterfly labs.
給butterfly labs.
I purchased, basically, a custom-designed
我買了一台客製化的
Bitcoin-mining supercomputer.
超級比特幣礦機
If Bitcoin fails...
比特幣一旦失敗...
Everything I have is worthless.
那這些都會變得沒有價值
The Bitcoins I have,
包括我持有的比特幣,
the computers, the mining system
那些電腦跟礦機
was all a waste of money.
就等於把錢浪費掉了.
But if it succeeds, then...
但如果成功...
It will have been worth it, I think.
那這些努力就會有價值, 希望啦.
- - The Bitcoin economy was a wild west in cyberspace
-  比特幣就如同 網路上的大荒野
that was very attractive to hackers and scammers.
對於駭客與騙子來說 非常有吸引力.
Over the years, tens of thousands of coins had been stolen
幾年內, 數以萬計的比特幣失竊
and 2012 proved no different.
而到了2012年也是一樣.
Users had to be careful.
使用者必須非常小心.
If somebody steals your Bitcoins, there are no consumer protections.
如果某個人偷了你的比特幣 沒有任何的消費者保護措施.
Sorry, they're gone. You lost your Bitcoins? They're gone
抱歉,他們就消失了. 你遺失了比特幣？他們不見了.
and you're not going to get them back.
而且你再也拿不回來了
But after months of stagnation on the exchanges,
但是經過了幾個月的停滯,
the Bitcoin price was on the rise again.
比特幣匯率再次提升.
The price of Bitcoin today is around $7 U.S.D.,
這時比特幣匯率來到7美元,
which just had a nice little bump this week.
這禮拜有了好的趨勢
By the end of the year, the blogging site Wordpress
到了年末, 著名的部落格系統wordpress
announced it would start accepting Bitcoin payments.
宣布他們將接受比特幣支付.
And in early 2013, the discussion forum Reddit
在2013年初 美國著名論壇reddit
also announced Bitcoin support.
也宣布接受比特幣支付.
They were the first major sites to incorporate Bitcoin,
他們是早期接受比特幣的主要網站,
and these milestones signaled the beginning
這同時也宣告了一個
of mainstream acceptance.
比特幣邁向主流的里程碑.
Bitcoin is the most subversive technology on the planet.
比特幣是目前最顛覆的技術
This is a system that is growing around the entire world.
這是一個全球性成長的系統
So if it works, if this experiment continues to grow,
如果他繼續像這樣持續發展
it doesn't just help a few of us in this state or in the country,
不只可以幫助到這州或是這個國家的少數人
but it actually helps everyone around the world.
基本上可以幫助到 世界上的每個人.
As the Bitcoin price hovered around
比特幣的價格依然徘徊
it's previous all-time high of $31,
直到他的歷史新高,31美元
I visited a libertarian conference in New Hampshire.
我參加了一個New Hampshire的 自由主義者會議.
It lost 20% and then it gained 20%
在20分鐘以內 他跌了20%,
in 20 minutes.
又漲了20%
It is-- They're silly.
真的是- 太離譜了.
Libertarians are among
自由主義者幾乎是
the earliest adopters of Bitcoin.
最早的比特幣使用者.
Its nature as a currency that isn't controlled
無法被中央政府控制的特質
by central banks makes it attractive to this community.
使其受到這些社群的歡迎.
Once I was able to kind of grok the basic concept,
自從我了解比特幣的基本特性,
it was like, "this is the perfect money."
我就想說 "這是最完美的貨幣啊"
This is what a Bitcoin address looks like.
比特幣的地址看起來像這樣.
Think of this long string of characters
可以想像成由字母構成
as an account number where your Bitcoins are stored.
的一個比特幣帳號.
When you send or receive Bitcoins,
當你傳送比特幣,
they are sent to these addresses.
他們是被傳送到這些地址.
The addresses are long and hard to remember
這些地址很長並難以記得
so using a phone to scan a Q.R. Code
所以可以使用手機及QRcode
is a fast and easy way to read them.
讓傳送比特幣變得又快又簡單
Another good thing to know
另一個比特幣的特點
is that Bitcoins can be broken down
就是比特幣可以被拆解
to eight decimal places.
到小數點後八位.
This means that you can send fractions of a Bitcoin.
這代表你可以傳送很微量的金額.
So any amount of money can be represented.
任何數量的金額都可以被表現出來.
With Bitcoin, every transaction is public.
在使用比特幣時,所有的
Everyone can see the amount that is being sent
交易記錄都會被公開,任何人都可以
without necessarily knowing the identity of the sender.
看到交易金額,卻不知道使用者是誰.
These guys even have one of the first Bitcoin ATMs.
這些人甚至設計了 第一台比特幣ATM
You just scan your Q.R. Code on your phone,
你只要掃描你的QRcode,
put in the dollar bills and press the button.
插入紙鈔並按下按鈕.
Bam. Done. Perfect.
- 然後就好了 - 真完美.
You now traded your worthless piece of paper
你已經把你無價值的紙片
for real currency.
換成了真正的貨幣.
It's like, "end the fed?" It's like, seriously, you think
聽起來就像"關了聯邦儲備", 然後你說真的嗎？
you're gonna end the fed? You're not gonna end the fed.
你真的要關了儲備銀行？ 你辦不到的.
You're not gonna change anything about the fed.
你不可能改變聯邦儲備的什麼事情.
- Transcend the fed. - Bypass the fed.
- 滲透聯邦儲備. - 繞過聯邦儲備.
- Right, yeah. - That's what you should do.
- 對啊沒錯. - 那就是你應該做的.
My concern is how the governments will react.
我注意的地方是 銀行會如何反應.
They can't kill or stop Bitcoin,
他們沒辦法關閉或是停止 比特幣,
but they could impede it and they could get in the way of its development.
但是他們可以干擾他, 或是他們可以滲透進去開發.
A few weeks later across the ocean,
幾個星期以後,在海的另一邊
a financial crisis was reaching a breaking point
一場經濟災難在塞浦路斯
on the island of Cyprus.
發生了.
Cyprus is on the brink of going bust.
這個地方即將破產
The rest of Europe has agreed to a bailout,
歐洲其他國家同意救援,
but only if Cyprus raids people's bank accounts for quick hard cash.
但是塞浦路斯必須從人民的帳戶中拿錢出來.
People tried to get money out of the cash machines
民眾想要從提款機中領錢
but electronic transfers have been stopped.
但是電子交易已經暫停.
Never did I think that they would...
- 我從來沒有想到這些銀行...
...in a completely unprecedented manner
...用一種前所未見的方式
resort to stealing money
從人民的帳戶裡面
from people's bank accounts.
直接偷走金錢
The Cypriots had placed their trust
塞浦路斯人民曾經相信 銀行系統
in the banking system and it had failed them.
但是他們從此失去信任
As news of the crisis spread around the world,
當經濟崩潰的新聞在全球傳播,
Bitcoin believers were quick to point it out
比特幣的支持者們 很快的就指出
as an example of why a currency
為什麼我們需要一種
free from government control was needed.
不受政府控制的貨幣.
There's actually Bitcoin ATMs
當時在塞浦路斯還出現了
apparently being set up in Cyprus.
比特幣ATM
All of a sudden, Bitcoin looks
忽然之間,大家忽然覺得比特幣
like an attractive prospect.
是一種具有希望的願景.
While this was happening in Cyprus,
當塞浦路斯發生事件的同時,
regulators at the U.S. treasury
美國財政部的監管機構
weighed in on Bitcoin.
也正密切注意著比特幣.
The financial crimes enforcement network, known as FinCEN,
金融犯罪執法網路,簡稱Fincen
issued its first regulatory guidance on virtual currencies.
發佈了第一個數位貨幣的監管說明.
The guidance implied that Bitcoin,
該說明指出比特幣本身,
in and of itself, was not illegal.
與其相關交易行為並不違法.
It was the perfect storm.
這正是一場完美風暴.
The situation in Cyprus suggested
塞浦路斯這樣的事件 顯示了
that Bitcoin could function as a financial safe haven.
比特幣作為貨幣安全港的可能性.
And the approving nod of U.S. regulators
而美國監管機構的許可
was a green light for investors.
對於投資者正是一張通行證.
The Market agreed
市場也開始反應
and the exchange price continued to climb.
而匯率則繼續往上攀升.
It's moving from the super super-early-adopter phase
我們正從 非常非常早的使用階段
to possibly the early-adopter phase.
進入到早期使用階段
Bitcoin was getting
比特幣開始受到
international exposure
國際矚目
and people were starting to pay attention.
而人們也開始注意起來.
This is actually a live, updated map of the globe
這是一張全球的及時地圖
and the lines represent Bitcoin clients.
這些線條就代表 比特幣的客戶端(node).
Basically where the Bitcoin software is running.
也表示哪裡有比特幣軟體正在運作.
And the length of the line determines
線條的長度則表示
how long it's been online or how active it's been.
他已經上線多久 或是他的活躍程度
And every time I look at this,
每次當我看這張地圖
I swear it gets more and more saturated.
我覺得這個地圖越來越豐富
You can almost see an outline of the U.S. now.
你幾乎可以看到美國的樣子了
South America-- You're starting to get it.
南美洲-- 也正在開始發展.
But the big news, in my opinion,
但在我的觀察, 最重要的是在...
is this-- China.
這裡--中國.
You used to see one, two, three, maybe.
你以前大概只會看到 一個兩個三個.
And this is all within the last three weeks or so.
但是這些都是過去三個禮拜 出現的.
That's the most I've ever seen in China.
是我目前看到中國的數量 最多的時候.
Look down here. Indonesia, Singapore,
然後往下看 印尼, 新加坡,
Australia, New Zealand.
澳洲, 紐西蘭.
The following week it snowed in Pittsburg.
接下來幾週, pittsburg都在下雪.
I was eagerly awaiting the delivery of two Avalon ASICs,
我焦急的等待著 我的avalon asics,
state of the art computers
這些電腦搭載的是
with chips specifically designed for mining Bitcoins.
專門設計來"挖礦"的特殊晶片.
Yifu Guo is at the forefront
Yifu guo 是一位
of the new generation of hardware,
新世代硬體的先驅,
and is the first to bring them to Market.
也是首位將這些機器推出市場的人.
Everybody, including myself,
所有人,包含我在內
had severely underestimated
都完全的低估了
the mining Market and how big it is.
這個礦機市場的規模
When Bitcoin began,
在比特幣發展初期,
a standard laptop was powerful enough
一台標準筆電 已經可以在幾天內
to mine hundreds of Bitcoins in a matter of days.
挖出數以百計的比特幣.
The technology evolved rapidly over the past couple of years.
這項科技在過去幾年內 日益月新.
A lot of people are getting into it
有更多的人投入
or still trying to catch up.
或是試圖趕上趨勢
I was on vacation with my family
當我的新礦機送到時
when the new miners were scheduled to arrive.
我剛好正在與我的家人度假.
The price of Bitcoin had rocketed to $77
這時,比特幣的匯率衝到77美元
so I asked some friends to wait at my house
所以我請朋友在我家幫忙代收
to get them running as soon as possible.
而且要盡快裝起來.
All right!
-  太好了!
- I hope this is good. I hope it's worthwhile. - Oh, definitely.
- 我希望這是好東西  應該很值得吧. - 當然
These are new computer parts here...
這些是新的電腦零件...
- Excellent, excellent. - ...Fresh in from China.
- 太好了,太好了. - ...從中國送來的.
- - All right, it's not official until you sign.
來吧,在你還沒簽名以前 不算送到.
There we go.
那就簽吧.
Yeah, we'll see. Maybe down the road
- 我希望以後你們也可以
you guys will start accepting Bitcoin one day, I bet.
開始接受比特幣支付.
- That's cool. -  Just a matter of time.
- 聽起來不錯. - 只是時間的問題.
Good luck to you guys. All right.
- 祝你們順利. - 謝啦.
I notified Dan
我剛剛通知Dan了
and he has a little response here.
然後這是他的回應.
Welcome to the financial renaissance.
歡迎來到金融革命.
192.168.1.140.
192.168.1.140.
255.255.255.0.
255.255.255.0.
192.168.1.1.
192.168.1.1.
That's the default gateway.
那是預設閘道.
My first pull is gonna be stratum. ozc.in, port 3333.
我的第一個礦池會是 stratum.Ozc.In, port 3333.
Port 80, but I can do 3333.
Port 80, 但是我也可以用 3333.
And when everything's all said and done, for at least a little while,
雖然花了點時間, 但所有東西都弄好了
it should be pulling in 10 to 12 coins a day.
他每天應該會產生 10到12個比特幣
That's gonna change though, after another week.
過兩個禮拜就會變了
It's gonna get dropped down to, like, eight,
大概會掉到8個吧,
- just because the difficulty's just going through the roof. - Yeah.
- 因為全網難度會提高. - 對啊.
Everybody's firing these things up,
很多人開始加入了,
so it's always a race to stay ahead
所以你要贏在前面
and try to be the first guy with the hardware, you know?
而且最好是第一批買到這些機器的人?
Oh, I'm getting pings. Whoo!
喔,我ping到他了. 太好了
Yup, we're kicking.
好喔,我們已經開始了.
We are accepting shares.
我們開始分得獲利了.
It is live.
上線了.
We've got the Merlot!
我們可以開Merlot了!
Hey, that looks like Johan.
嘿,那是johan耶.
Say, "I'm going to college 'cause my dad mines Bitcoins."
來說, "我爸用挖來的比特幣付我的大學學費."
Dad going Bitcoins.
爸爸要比特幣.
So, big day today, huh?
今天是個重要的日子?
Big day. Look at that. 104.
是大日子. 你看這個 104(美元).
Current Bitcoin price. Broke 100 today.
比特幣的匯率 在今天突破100美元.
It is April fool's day.
今天也是愚人節.
The price rising so insanely high
價格一直往上漲
is kind of a little bit unprecedented,
真的令人意想不到,
so-- I mean, it's bound to pop a little bit.
我是認為他會再漲一些的
Maybe. I don't know.
也許吧,也說不定
Maybe it'll be at 225 in a week and a half,
也許過了一週半就會漲到255,
so who knows? Bitcoin styles--
但誰知道? 這就是比特幣--
Could go up, could go down.
可能會漲, 也可能會跌.
As the price passed 100,
當匯率來到100的時候,
we took a trip to visit Gavin Andresen.
我們去找了 Gavin andresen.
He is known to have worked closely with Satoshi
他因為在早期與satoshi共同工作
during Bitcoin's early days.
而眾所皆知.
Here's the train tracks, and he did say
這邊有些鐵路, 他之前跟我說
there would be train tracks maybe passing through.
到他家會經過鐵路.
Here we go. This is Gavin's house.
我們到了. 這就是Gavin的家.
Gavin is one of the last people
在satoshi消失之前,
to communicate with Satoshi before he disappeared.
Gavin是其中一個跟他通訊的人.
Morning. This is my brother Nick
早安. 這是我的兄弟 Nick
- and his wife Ashley. - Nice to meet you.
- 還有他太太 Ashley. - 很高興認識你.
- Hi, nice to meet you.
-  Hi, 我也是.
Found the place okay, so-- - good.
這個地方感覺很不錯-- - 很好.
We're very excited to be here.
我們也很開心來到這邊
Come in. This is my humble house.
請進 歡迎來到寒舍.
- That's where I work. This is where I live.
- - 那是我工作的地方. 這是我日常居住的地方.
- Beautiful home. - Well, thanks.
- 真是漂亮的家. - 謝謝.
A little higher, please. Right there.  Great.
- 麻煩調亮一點. - 就是這樣.
Got it.
-  搞定.
How did you first get into Bitcoin?
你是如何接觸到比特幣的?
Tell us a little bit of the story of how you got involved.
告訴大家你怎麼樣開始的.
I had been working at UMass
我曾經在馬薩諸塞大學
as a staff programmer
的電腦科學研究部門
in the computer science
擔任程式設計師
department research group.
的工作
My wife's a Professor at UMass.
我太太則是那間大學的教授.
I actually quit that job before going
我離職以後,
on a six-month sabbatical in Australia.
去澳洲度了6個月的假.
I just happened to read a little blurb
我有一次讀到一篇部落格文章
online in somebody's blog
他提到了這個
that mentioned this Bitcoin project,
開放原始碼,跟金錢有關的
which is an open-source attempt to do money.
這個比特幣的計畫.
And it caught my interest.
然後我就開始研究了.
I basically just spent a few days
後來 我花了幾天的時間
read everything I could about it
去讀所有我能找到的文章
looked at the source code, downloaded the source code,
下載跟研究他的程式碼,
thought about it and I really couldn't convince myself
加以研究之後 我發現這是一個
that it would not work.
相當可行的東西.
It seemed like Satoshi had thought of everything.
看來satoshi已經想到所有的細節.
Since then...
從那以後...
I've just been sucked down the rabbit hole.
我就被深深吸引住了.
Bitcoin is open-source software.
比特幣 是一套開放程式碼軟體.
With open-source software,
任何人均可以看見,
the code is publicly available.
這類程式的程式碼.
Anyone can look at it and see how it runs.
並研究其如何運作.
And they can also contribute their own changes.
而且他們也可以貢獻 自己修改的版本.
Programmers like Gavin were able to join Satoshi to work on Bitcoin
這就是Gavin這類的工程師 如何加入開發行列的方式
simply because they were interested.
單純因為興趣使然.
Over time, I think Satoshi learned to trust me.
隨著時間過去, satoshi也開始信任我.
He could see that I didn't make very many stupid mistakes.
他看到我沒有犯下離譜的錯誤.
I never had any personal connection with Satoshi.
我跟satoshi沒有任何私人交集.
It was always purely business.
我們談的都是公事.
And I think that's because he was so worried about
我想他也是擔心
people finding out his identity.
有人發現他的身份.
I don't know why. My last email to him
我不知道原因. 我最後一次mail給他
was telling him that I had
是提到我同意去
agreed to go visit the folks at the C.I.A.,
跟一些CIA的人會面
so...
所以...
Whether that had something to do with him
我不知道這個跟他
deciding to cut off communication with me entirely--
完全跟我斷絕聯絡 有沒有關係--
He had been pulling away before then,
他之前已經保持距離,
but the C.I.A. Invited me to come talk at the C.I.A.
但是我還是同意
And I agreed to do that.
去CIA與他們談談.
Knowing it would surely spark
知道一定會被謠傳
conspiracy theories, Gavin posted an announcement
陰謀論之類的事, 為了除去謠言,
on the Bitcoin talk discussion forum
Gavin 在比特幣論壇
to head off any rumors.
發表了一篇聲明.
Having taken on the lead developer position
當satoshi消失之後
since Satoshi's disappearance,
Gavin成為主要的開發人員,
Gavin found himself facing an increasing number of responsibilities
他發現自己承擔的責任
and public scrutiny.
與大眾關注越來越多.
Do your neighbors know that you're kind of at the center
你的鄰居知道你在 這個嶄新科技裡面
of one of the most disruptive technologies?
擔任要角嗎?
I think-- I think they know that I do this wacky Bitcoin project.
我猜他們應該知道 我很熱衷於比特幣.
I don't think they know quite how big it is yet.
但他們應該不知道 這個規模有多大.
Right now,
現在,
Bitcoin's a billion-dollar project.
比特幣是一個 價值數十億的案子.
When I started it was this tiny little experiment.
當我開始的時候 他只是一個實驗品.
And as it gets bigger,
當他越來越有規模,
the pressure to not screw up
那種 "絕對不能搞砸"
just gets bigger and bigger.
的壓力也越來越大
Two weeks later
兩個星期以後
the price soared past 150.
匯率來到150美元.
And some Bitcoiners woke up
有一些比特幣持有者
to find out they were Bitcoin millionaires.
發現他們變成了 百萬富翁.
23-year-old Charlie Shrem
23歲的Charlie shrem
is the C.E.O. of a company called Bitlnstant.
是bitinstant公司的執行長.
Bitlnstant was one of the first startups in the Bitcoin space.
Bitinstant 是比特幣領域 起頭的少數公司.
In Bitcoin's infancy, people had to jump
比特幣發展初期
through several hoops to buy them.
為了到mt. Gox買比特幣.
One of the only ways
你必須要把錢中轉好幾次
was through the Mt. Gox exchange,
才能買得到,
but this process required transferring money
但這種方式必須花費
through several intermediaries
好幾週的時間
and could take weeks.
讓錢經過好幾個地方.
Charlie launched Bitlnstant to streamline this process.
Charlie創辦bitinstant 的目的就是要簡化流程.
And to help people buy Bitcoins quickly.
讓民眾可以快速買到比特幣.
Yeah, that's good. That's great.
看起來很棒,很好.
-  That's pretty nice. - You go like that.
- 很不錯. - 你要像這樣.
Yeah, sure.
當然.
Today Charlie is being photographed
Charlie正在為
for an article in "Businessweek."
businessweek的一篇專訪拍照
One of the ideas they had
他們提出的一個點子
was that you're going-- Throwing stuff up in the air
是感覺你好像在往上丟東西
and they were gonna add Bitcoins in later on.
那他們之後會加上比特幣.
- Going like that? -  Yeah.
- 喜歡嗎? - 不錯啊.
This Bitcoin thing can actually change the world.
比特幣是一個可以改變世界的技術.
But for this thing to succeed,
要讓他成功的第一件事情,
we have to figure out a way to get more money
就是找到一種
in and out of the ecosystem.
讓他容易流通的方式.
Look out the window a bit. Totally-- yeah.
往窗外看一點. 就是這樣
Then you can look-- Yeah, that's good.
然後你再看-- 對,很好.
And not show that I'm super stressed out right now
而且我要看起來 沒那麼緊張
and we have thousands of orders that are being processed
因為我們有幾千筆交易要做
and I'm bugging out, trying to get the new site launched.
而我最近還要上線 新版的網站
-  No, don't look like that. - It's crazy.
- 眼神不要那樣. - 真是瘋狂.
I'm trying not to, but it's really hard.
我盡量不會,但實在有點難.
Things have been insane.
事情變得很棘手.
I haven't slept in days.
我已經好幾天沒睡了.
The price is just rising, so a lot of people
價格還在攀升
are putting money into it.
所以很多人都在買.
Normally, Charlie can get Bitcoins
通常,Charlie
to his customers in about an hour.
可以讓他的顧客 在一小時內獲得比特幣.
But with the recent flood of people
但是因為有大量
trying to purchase Bitcoins,
的購買交易,
Bitlnstant can't fill their orders fast enough.
使得bitinstant無法即時處理交易.
When I pulled up our customer service interface,
當我打開客戶服務系統,
we have close to 2,000 open tickets.
大概有兩千個待處理的請求.
And that's just from Saturday to this morning.
而且只是從星期六到今天早上的.
Nobody was ready
沒有人準備好
for this kind of volume,
可以處理這麼多的訂單,
so we're trying to catch up
所以我們在盡量提高速度
with the volume and keep everybody happy.
讓每個人都滿意.
Man on phone: Can you just sort of describe quickly
你可以形容一下
what the last week or so has been like for you guys?
過去兩週你們的狀況嗎?
The last week or so saw our support staff
過去幾個禮拜, 我們的客服人員
go from two people to five people.
從兩個人變成五個人.
When someone offers you
當某人提供你
a seat on the rocket,
一個火箭上的座位
you don't ask where the seat is.
你不會問這個位子在哪,
You just get on the rocket.
而是你會直接跳上去
Further, our volume has basically tripled
再來,我們的交易量
in the past two weeks,
在過去兩週內變成三倍,
going from a few hundred transactions a day
從每天只有幾百筆
to now two, three thousand transactions a day.
到現在一天兩三千筆
-  You just came onboard here, right? - Yeah, I did.
你是新來的? - 對啊.
Actually, today is kinda my first day.
其實今天是我第一天上班.
-  Oh really? - Yeah.
- 真的? - 對啊.
How does it feel to be a part of all this madness?
進入這一個瘋狂的世界 感覺如何?
Um, well, madness, yeah.
喔,真的很瘋狂.
It's overwhelming.
真是撲天蓋地而來.
And what do you do for Bitlnstant?
那你在bitinstant做什麼?
I'm the C.F.O.
我是財經長
Man on phone: Can you give me a daily estimate
你可以給我一個
of how much money you're moving through your system?
每天經過你們處理的 大概的現金數量?
Um, it's in the--
恩,每天大概--
In the six figures every day.
有六位數的金額
All right. Well, thanks, Charlie.
那先這樣. 謝謝你, Charlie.
-  I really appreciate it. - Thank you.
- 我也很感謝. - 謝謝.
I don't know how the government will react to Bitcoin,
我不知道政府對 比特幣會有什麼反應,
but I spend thousands of dollars on lawyers every day
但是我每天花了 幾千塊的律師費
just to make sure that I'm not gonna go to jail.
就為了避免牢獄之災.
It's super terrifying. I mean, I don't wanna go to jail.
真的有點擔心. 我怕被關起來.
I don't wanna become a martyr either.
我還不想變成烈士.
Bitcoin was the talk of the town.
比特幣開始成為熱門話題.
Charlie was in the limelight
Charlie也處在風頭上
and could barely keep up with media requests.
差點應付不來媒體的好奇詢問.
Within hours, the price passed $200.
幾個小時內, 價格衝破200美元.
First day of spring,
春天剛降臨,
first day Bitcoin is over 200.
也是首次衝破200元.
The start of a new era.
也是一個新時代的開始.
Hi. Nice to meet you.
Hi. 很高興認識你.
I'm the nice warm loving mom
我是讓他住在這裡
that makes him live at home.
的好媽媽
'Cause we can't-- We can't part from him yet.
因為我們離不開他.
We love him too much.
我們太愛他了.
This is where it all started
這就是起源地
and this is where it still goes down.
也就是一些事情的終點.
I've been collecting money from all over the world.
我以前在蒐集各地的紙鈔.
And it's just something I did way before Bitcoin.
這是在接觸比特幣之前.
I've been doing it since I was a kid.
而且我從小就開始蒐集了.
So it's funny that I'm collecting all this...
所以我在蒐集這些沒什麼...
Fiat that's not worth anything
價值的紙鈔貨幣
and then all of a sudden I get into this Bitcoin thing.
然後我就開始接觸比特幣了.
I realized during high school that
我高中的時候
I could never work for anyone.
發現我沒辦法替人工作.
I made up a term--
我創造了一個精神科用詞--
Psychologically unemployable.
精神狀態無法被雇用.
I started Bitlnstant while I was still
我在大學一開始
in my senior year of college.
就創辦了bitinstant.
Bitcoin currently is the largest social-economic experiment
比特幣是目前在經濟社會上
ever conducted in the history of the world.
有史以來最大的實驗.
2013, possibly 2014,
2013年, 或者是 2014年,
will be the two years that really make or break Bitcoin.
將會是比特幣最有突破的兩年.
Bitcoin is the first product that's digital,
比特幣是一個數位化, 但也是
but it's also scarce.
相對稀少的產品.
I got some good news last night that
我昨晚得知一個好消息
part of our licensing deals that we've been trying to do
過去幾個月我們在申請一堆許可
for the past few months are finally,
現在應該
hopefully, coming through.
可以準備發出來了.
We got approved to be licensed
我們允許在48個州的30個州
in 30 of the 48 states in money transmission.
進行金錢交易
I've been working very hard on trying to be compliant
我很努力的在遵守各種法規
in the legal realm
之前fincen的公告
and with FinCEN's announcement,
使得比特幣公司,
setting up a way for Bitcoin companies to legally exist,
可以正式合法經營,
that really changes the whole game of Bitcoin.
這真的改變了整個大局.
And for us, it helped us get that last push
對於我們來說
that we needed from all the banks
那正是說服各銀行合作的因素
and the regulators to finally, hopefully,
之後希望就是監管機構,
get that licensing that we need.
然後拿到那些許可.
Today, Charlie's meeting with a realtor
這天, Charlie為了新的辦公室
to talk about new office space.
跟一個房屋仲介見面.
Hi, Charlie, nice to meet you.
Hi, Charlie, 很高興認識你.
- Hi, I'm Mitch Waldman. How are you? - A pleasure.
- Hi, 我是 Mitch waldman. -你好嗎?  - 真是榮幸.
- Got a minute? - I have 10 minutes for you.
- 有時間嗎? - 我可以給你10分鐘.
We're-- we're a company with no boss, essentially.
我們公司不算是有老闆.
Everyone has their responsibilities.
每個人都有自己的職責.
It's just one big executive board.
有點像是一個大的董事會.
- It's just one big executive board. - Okay.
- 一個大的董事會. - 瞭解.
If I don't do my job, these guys are all gonna yell at me.
如果我不做事, 這些人也會罵我.
So that's how we do it, but we get things done. - Waldman: All right.
-  所以這就是我們做事的方式. 好的.
We're outgrowing this space, as you can see here.
你可以看到 這個地方快要裝不下了.
- That's a good problem to have. - Yes.
- 這是個好的問題. - 對啊.
Now Rachel said there was a great concern
Rachel說他有一個擔憂
- about security in this space. -  Yeah.
- 就是這裡的保全問題. 對.
We're regulated, so we can't share an office
我們有些限制, 所以我們不能
- with another company if they have access to us. - I get that.
- 跟其他公司共用空間 - 我瞭解.
Our asset is our software.
我們的系統就是資產.
Our software is processing hundreds of thousands of dollars a day
我們的系統每天處理數千美金
instantly. Really quickly.
即時, 非常的快.
And that's on-site here? Or is it in the cloud?
那是在這邊? 還是在雲端處理?
No, this is in the cloud. It's all in the cloud, but we monitor--
沒,那是在雲端. 當然是在雲端--
We have to monitor everything from here...
但是我們要在這邊監控...
Right. -...And debug, fix, take down, upload more--
- 是. - ...然後除蟲,下載,上傳--
- Put up more workers. - We deal with high-volume data-oriented stuff every day.
- 啟動更多的程式. - 我們每天處理大量的資料.
Very very sensitive customer data.
而且是非常敏感的客戶資料.
If there were not a doorman,
如果沒有保全的話,
at the very least the space would be designed in such a manner
那起碼可以弄成一個
that there'd be a locked reception area.
跟接待處獨立分隔的空間
If we want to pursue a guard at some point,
如果我們需要一個警衛,
we could have them in that area.
那我們就會讓他在那邊.
I absolutely think
- - 而且我覺得
- It will be at some point. It's just a matter of time. -  Really?
- 那是遲早的事. - 真的?
The potential for theft is huge.
對於竊賊來說很可觀的事.
It's like operating a bank, essentially.
我們差不多就是在開銀行.
That's pretty much it.
真的像是那樣.
- Gotcha. - It's basic stuff.
- 瞭解了. - 那是基本概念啦.
Yup yup. All right.
好, 我知道了.
Any other words for me?
還有我需要知道的嗎?
- Okay. - Are you willing to handle the task?
- 好吧. - 那你想要接下來嗎?
Sign me up, captain.
報到,船長.
That night, the price got as high as $266.
那天晚上, 匯率到了266美元的新高.
Every major news outlet had taken notice.
主要的新聞媒體都注意到了.
Bitcoin fever was at an all-time high.
前所未有的比特幣熱潮.
It is getting a lot of attention.
真的有很多人注意.
People are fascinated by anything that makes new highs
群眾對比特幣的新事物
every day for weeks on end, which Bitcoin has done.
造成了比特幣的匯率成長.
In terms of the total number of the people
我沒辦法告訴你
using the currency, I'm not sure,
有多少人在使用這種貨幣,
but you can say that there's a huge amount
但我可以告訴你
of fluctuation in the volume of trading.
已經出現大批的交易量.
And then the price crashed.
接著,價格崩盤.
Bitcoin lost more than half of its value
在六個小時內
in six hours.
跌了超過一半.
From craze to crash.
從瘋狂到狂瀉.
It's the talk of many people in the blogosphere,
在部落格中被討論著,
and it's certainly suffering some growing pains.
而現在遇到了成長的痛楚.
The value of the virtual currency Bitcoin has plunged.
比特幣的價值正在狂跌.
It's been a crazy day today.
今天真是瘋狂的一天.
I haven't slept in like 40 hours.
我已經40個小時沒睡覺.
Your order processed. I don't understand
你的訂單已經處理了. 我不明白
why we're still having this conversation.
為什麼我們還要有這樣的對話.
We refunded your order. We sent you extra Bitcoins.
我們退回你的訂單了. 還送你一些比特幣了.
I don't care, man.
我不管那麼多.
When it comes to my money, I don't fuck around.
那是我的錢, 我不跟你打迷糊仗.
I know, man. You need your stuff.
- 我知道. - 你要你的東西.
I hear ya, I hear ya. It processed.
我聽到了,我聽到了 已經處理了.
Your Bitcoins are there, man.
你的比特幣就在啊.
So, Charlie, what's been going on today?
Charlie,今天怎樣了?
-  Crazy day, huh? - Yeah, Mt. Gox--
- 瘋狂的一天? - 對啊, mt. Gox--
Their whole system pretty much failed
他們的系統整個失靈
and their whole trading engine is broken.
而交易系統也故障了
Pretty much caused-- almost-- Us to shut down for the day.
幾乎讓我們--接近--關門了吧.
Further, the Bitcoin price has just been
還有,今天比特幣的匯率
wildly swinging up and down
瘋狂起伏
it was down $100 today.
今天已經跌了100美金.
It's gaining back up, but mostly because people can't buy and sell
有在恢復, 但是大部分人還不能買賣
and they can't withdraw and they can't deposit.
他們也不能存款,跟存款
'Cause the whole thing is just-- it's just a Fritz.
感覺就是Fritz事件一樣
So what we're trying to do is figure out a way
所以我們在找一個新的平台
to mitigate orders somewhere else for now.
然後把訂單移過去處理.
With Mt. Gox stuck in a nosedive,
隨著mt. Gox事件發生,
the ripple effect is creating chaos in the Bitcoin Markets.
連鎖效應造成了 比特幣市場恐慌.
I'm trying to figure out
我正在試圖了解
why our orders aren't going through.
我們的訂單卡住的原因.
Rachel, am I allowed to take another Advil
Rachel我一個小時拿過advil了
if I took one an hour ago?
但是我可以再拿一個嗎?
They've been having problems ordering anything off of Gox.
他們在處理gox的訂單問題.
Yeah, I'm getting a lot of customers emailing,
對,我收到一堆客戶的email說,
saying "it says 'executed, ' but it's not showing in the blockchain."
訂單顯示"已訂購", 但是沒出現在blockchain中.
Dude, Gox suspended trading.
嘿, gox 暫停交易了.
- Really? - Yeah.
- 真的? - 對.
"Orders placed suspended until 2100."
"在2100前都暫停交易."
What time-- What's 2100?
什麼時間-- 什麼2100?
What? That's 9:00 P.M. oh my God.
什麼? 那是晚上9:00. 我的天啊.
If you bought at 150...
如果你在150的時候買...
And then you're at 260,
然後到了260,
and then you watch it dip down back to 150,
接著你又看著他回到150,
do you panic some? Yeah, absolutely.
那你會緊張嗎? 那是當然的啦.
I don't know what a Bitcoin is. I just bought it.
因為你根本不知道比特幣是什麼. 結果還買了.
Fuck.
幹.
You see buy orders, people buying
你看到訂單, 大家買進
and selling at such a wide range.
又大筆賣出.
It doesn't make any sense.
根本沒道理.
The a.P.I. Is just constantly failing?
API一直處理失敗?
Is that what's going on? Or are we're not getting any orders.
就是這個狀況嗎? 而且我們會損失訂單.
Don't care about the price.
先不要管價格.
Speculators can play musical chairs
懷疑論者可以整天
all day long for all I care.
講一些有的沒的.
I'm-I'm-- I'm long.
我都習慣了.
I was focused on expanding my mining operation.
我主力則放在提升挖礦能力.
The only people that are gonna be shaken out
那些對價格恐慌的人
by this drop
通常都是
are people that are new to Bitcoin.
比特幣的新手.
Here's the Avalons, spinning away,
avalons在這邊全速運轉,
mining away.
繼續挖礦.
And if everything goes as planned,
如果一切按照計畫的話,
we'll have 18 more of these guys
我們在幾個星期內會再有
in a couple of weeks.
18台這種機器.
Bitcoin is a complicated thing.
比特幣很複雜.
You have to spend some time looking into it
你需要花時間深入了解
and understanding it before you really care.
並在你真的認識他之前多多理解他.
Now there's droves of people that--
現在有一堆人因為他的價格很高--
You know, are giving it more than just that glance,
,而且完全不理解他的原理
because the price has gone so high.
,就直接跳進來
And they have dollar signs in their eyes like Uncle scrooge.
而且眼裡跟守財奴唐老鴨一樣的充滿錢號.
It's so much more than that,
除了價值以外還有很多事情,
and I think that's why the people who are mining
我想這也是那些挖礦的人
and the people who believe in it
跟那些相信的人
are just kind of holding strong.
就繼續持有的理由.
When trading resumed at Mt. Gox,
當mt. Gox系統恢復時,
the price fell even further, to around $70.
價格進一步下滑到70美元.
71 on B.T.C.-E.
bTC-E上面是71美元.
Yeah, Bitcoin-- It's volatile.
對啊,比特幣正在蒸發.
It's gonna be a long time until we have stability.
很久以後我們才會看到他的穩定期.
That's the nature of the beast.
就跟自然的野獸一樣.
Price discovery can be violent and volatile.
價格可能會猛力蒸發.
There's gonna be a lot of people that come and go,
一堆人進來然後離開,
and people that scream wolf.
還有一些人叫著狼來了.
But at the end of the day,
不過一天結束,
the only thing that really kind of stinks right now
對於持有者最介意的 就是大家
is that everybody is trading on one platform
都在同一個平台上面交易
that isn't doing the greatest job, so...
這不是一個很好的事情...
Over time, hopefully we'll see some more exchanges pop up
希望以後可以出現更多的交易所
and get some more options in.
以及更多的選擇.
People wanna keep using Bitcoin,
只要人們繼續用比特幣
I'm sure the infrastructure will come.
我相信這樣的架構會出現
It's just gotten ridiculously busy.
聽起來實在太扯
I get an email every two seconds now
但我每兩秒就收到一封email
and pretty much more email than I-- -
- 幾乎已經超過--
--Than I can keep up with.
--我的速度了.
Jered Kenna is the C.E.O. Of Tradehill.
Jered kenna是tradehill的執行長
The first U.S.-based Bitcoin exchange
他們是美國第一間
to compete with Mt. Gox.
與mt. Gox競爭的交易所
He's also on the list of Bitcoin millionaires.
他也在比特幣富翁的名單上.
This is Finnegan right here.
這是finnegan.
Guard dog. Hey, Finnegan.
警犬. 嘿, finnegan.
Jered runs Tradehill
Jered在一個名叫"20 mission"的
out of a 41-bedroom residential hotel
41個房間的旅館中經營tradehill
called 20 mission that he also owns.
這個地方是他所有.
We mostly rent out rooms to tech people, startup people.
我們通常租給科技人、新創公司
There's a lot of Bitcoiners.
也有不少比特幣玩家.
I actually accept rent in Bitcoin,
我也收比特幣付房租,
which is great, because we have a lot of international people.
當你有一堆國際訪客的時候 其實很方便.
* Bitcoin! *
¶ Bitcoin! ¶ （比特幣！）
* Came to us from the cryptogram *
¶ Came to us from the cryptogram ¶ （從加密學而來！）
* It came out of thin air *
¶ it came out of thin air ¶ （從虛無而來！）
* It saved us from those nasty dollars *
¶ it saved us from those nasty dollars ¶ （將我們從污金中救出）
* And won and yen *
¶ and won and yen ¶ （並獲得勝利）
* Bitcoin. *
¶ bitcoin. ¶ （比特幣！）
That's all I got. I'm done.
- 我只能想到這些. - 到這裡就好.
Digital currency is gonna happen.
數位貨幣將會發生.
I mean, it's-- it already is happening,
我是說, 他正在發生了
and it will be the future,
他會是未來的趨勢,
whether that's now,
不管是現在,
10 years from now, a hundred years from now.
10年後, 還是百年後.
We're going to be using digital currencies
我們都會用到 不需要依賴政府
that don't depend on fiat government.
的數位貨幣.
Jered originally launched Tradehill about two years ago,
Jered 兩年前創辦tradehill,
but ran into problems with a payment processor
但由於跟金流商發生問題
and was forced to shut down.
只好被迫關門.
Recently he met Ryan singer
最近 他遇到Ryan singer
and together they are relaunching the exchange.
而且一起重啟這個交易所.
The business we're in is
這個生意本身
helping people speculate, right?
就令人充滿疑問.
Markets are
市場本身
price discovery mechanisms.
就是價格導向機制.
That's what they're for.
這也是市場的目的.
People-- They buy, they sell,
每個人都在市場買賣,
there's the bid, there's the ask
這裡下單,那邊收單
and the price moves. And when it levels out,
接著價格就會變動. 然後平穩,
then that's what the Market price is.
那就是市場價格.
I can't even count the amount of people that have said,
我根本數不清有多少人跟我說過
"Bitcoin's not backed by anything.
"美金至少還有黃金擔保,
At least dollars are backed by gold."
但是比特幣什麼都沒有"
I've realized that a lot of people believe that.
而且我發現相信的人還不少.
My grandfather, he got me into investing
我的祖父在我五歲的時候,
when I was a kid. I was five years old.
就已經在教我投資.
I could explain a p/e ratio,
我可以解釋本益比,
and what a bid and an ask was,
買跟賣的定義,
and the difference between a limit order and a Market order
還有"限價單"跟"市價單"的差別
and all that stuff, so for me,
這類的東西. 對我來說,
I saw this as a way that the average person
我把這些視為 一般人可以控制自己經濟
could actually take control of their finances.
的一種方式
I just grew up pretty nerdy.
我從小其實還蠻怪的
I don't know. Then like at 15 years old,
我不知道耶, 好像到了15歲的時候,
I decided I didn't want to be a nerd anymore,
我忽然覺得自己不要那麼怪,
which was a mistake... 'Cause...
結果看起來好像錯了... 因為...
'Cause now I realize it's pretty awesome.
因為我覺得還不錯啊.
In 1999 I joined the marines.
我在1999年加入海軍.
I was originally with an engineering unit.
我原本是在工程單位.
2005, I went over to Afghanistan.
2005年的時候我到阿富汗.
I was mostly working with the Afghan national army.
基本上都跟阿富汗國軍工作.
It changed me a lot as a person.
對我自己改變了很多.
I've always been interested in economics
我對經濟、金融、科技
and finance and technology and cryptography.
與加密學 一直都很感興趣
I was in a cryptography forum
我那時候是在一個加密學論壇
and somebody I'd never met-- Who was anonymously
然後有個人, 我沒見過他也不知道他是誰
in this forum that I was chatting with--
這個人跟我說--
Sent me 10,000 Bitcoins
要送我一萬個比特幣
just as a way to test the system out
說是要測試系統
and see how it worked, and I got 'em.
並觀察運作情況, 然後我就拿到了.
I'm like, "that's cool, but what can I do with them?"
我那時候感覺, "好酷喔,但這些能做什麼?"
And he said, "well, nothing yet, but...
他就說, "目前沒什麼用...
If people believe it has value, it will."
但如果大家都相信他有價值, 那就會有."
At the time, there was really only one Bitcoin exchange
那時候其實只有一間交易所
it was Mt. Gox. I said, "we need an alternative.
就是 mt. Gox. 我就說,"我們需要另一個交易所
Who cares if the technology is decentralized
雖然說這個技術是分散式的
and the method of transfer is decentralized
傳送方式也是分散的
and the people are decentralized
群眾當然也是分散的
if all the trades are in the same location?"
但是大家都在同一個地方交易?"
I thought that building another exchange
我認為提供給人們
to give more people access to Bitcoin
另外一個比特幣交易所
would be a key part of Bitcoin's growth.
對比特幣的成長非常重要.
The day we launched, we got a quarter-million dollars in from user deposits.
我們開張那天 就有25萬美元的使用者存款
And we said, "oh shit, this is-- this is real.
然後我們說 "天啊,這是來真的了
Yeah.
嗨.
Hey.
嘿.
We're all fans of "The Big Lebowski,"
我們都很愛看the big lebowski (謀殺綠腳趾)
so we're gonna have a "Big Lebowski" party.
所以我們要弄個 big lebowski派對
Nice!
太好了!
It's a... Very exciting day.
真是個... 興奮的一天.
30 gallons of white Russian and hallway bowling.
30加侖的白俄羅斯雞尾酒 還有走廊保齡球
Yeah!
Yeah!
We work hard, but we party hard too.
我們努力工作, 但也努力的玩.
Okay. Okay, I'm good.
Okay. Okay, 我還好.
-  All right. - I'm good. I'm not dead.
- 那就好. - 我還好,我還沒死.
Yeah, I'm the first one in the house...
我其實是第一個住客...
That opened a Tradehill account.
也開了個tradehill帳號.
What happened?
後來怎麼了?
In the same day they went down to 90--
在一天內掉到剩下90(美元)--
$65 or something, or $90 a Bitcoin.
還是65還是90元的樣子
I stopped smiling.
我就笑不出來了.
Tradehill, round two, we optimized for success.
在Tradehill的第二階段成功計畫.
We launched expecting to have to do
希望我們的系統可以承載
hundreds of thousands of transactions a second.
每秒數以千計的交易量
Right now we've got about 15 people
我們現在有15個人
in addition to that, we've got about eight attorneys externally.
還要另外加上外面的8位律師.
A lot of people are depositing dollars.
很多人在存入美金.
A lot of people are depositing Bitcoin. We're getting more trading.
也有很多人在存比特幣. 現在有很多交易.
We're pushing that from a business perspective.
從商業觀點我們希望有更多(交易量).
Also, we're talking to people
我們也有跟一些人談
who want to do more automated trading on our platform.
有的人想要做自動交易
Get robots trading against each other.
讓機器人互相交易
We've stress tested this
我們還在做壓力測試
and we can handle about 500 times as much volume
我們現在可以承受的交易量大約
as Mt. Gox was seeing.
是mt. Gox的500倍
So we'll see what happens here.
然後我們再繼續觀察
The interest in us is pretty crazy.
我們的興趣真的很特別.
Just the news with Bitcoin
當新聞媒體開始到處談論
has really kind of validated everything.
比特幣之後
Now people are like, "oh, you're not this crazy person
現在大家不會再說 "你不是瘋了才研究
talking about some digital made-up currency."
這些虛構貨幣吧"
It's like, "oh, I've read about it in 'the wall street journal'
現在比較像是 "喔,我有在華爾街日報
and 'the New York times.' It's real."
還有時代雜誌看過,那是真的"
We had an investor come in
我們之前有一個金主來訪
and he said, "hey, I really appreciate
然後他說 "我真的很感謝你們
your scrappy nature and how you're hustling,
有這些非常純樸的設施, 還有你們的隨性
but I think it's time for you guys to spend 30 grand a month on rent.
但我真的覺得你們是時候 花個30塊去租個地方了.
When you have a billionaire client
當你有個百萬客戶
and they want to come check out your office
他們在投資你幾百萬之前
before they send you a multi-million dollar wire,
總會來看一下你的辦公室
asking them to walk past pawn shops
但是叫他們路過當鋪之類的
is not always the right feel.
- 聽起來總是不太對.
So we're leaving the mission. We're driving into Soma right now.
所以我們要離開那邊, 然後要找一個新的地方.
We're gonna go take a look at what may be our new office space
我們要去一個地方 看看未來可能的辦公室
pretty prestigious address-- One Market.
是個久負盛名地點-- One Market.
Right now we're trying to forge this path,
我們正在開拓這條路
and we're trying to comply with existing laws
所以不只是要符合現在的法規
and anticipate future laws,
還要注意未來的法律
which is extremely expensive and extremely difficult.
那會很困難而且很花錢
- Is there parking here? -  Yes.
- 這裡有停車位嗎? - 有.
Okay, is that included with--
OK,所以是包含在--
Of course.
當然沒有.
Right, what does that-- how much does-- -
- 對啦,但是那是多少--
How much does that cost?
要花多少錢啊?
That's not terrible.
沒那麼恐怖啦.
Whoa.
哇.
That's pretty sexy.
看起來很不賴嘛.
Twitter was here for over a year.
Twitter之前在這邊待過一年.
- Yeah. - Amazon comes and go every single year.
- 喔. - 亞馬遜也來過又走了.
- Oh, fantastic. - I have Macy's, I have J.C. Penney.
- 聽起來不錯. - 還有Macy's,以及j.C. Penney.
All the big ones, they come over.
這些都是大牌子.
They are part of the club.
大家都是同一夥的.
Sounds good. We'll be here tomorrow.
- 聽起來不錯. - 我們明天就來.
- Picking it up. - Thank you for the business.
- 我們在打包了. - 謝謝你.
- Thank you. - I appreciate it.
- 謝謝. - 我很感謝.
Thanks so much.
非常謝謝.
- We move in tomorrow. -  Just like--
- 我們明天就搬進去. - 感覺就像--
-  just like that, huh? - Just like that.
- 感覺就像怎樣? - 就這樣啊.
- That's how we roll. -  It's pretty surprising
- 這就是我們的方式. - 這麼快就敲定了
that that deal just happened so quickly.
真的令人有點意外
What was it? You just liked the space
原因是? 你喜歡那邊
and decided, "hey, there's no point in waiting"?
然後就覺得 "不用等了就這邊了?"
We like the space, we like the address.
我們喜歡這個地方還有地址
We just don't have the time to spend either.
而且我們沒有太多時間處理這個.
We've got all kinds of important stuff we're working on
而且我們手上還有 一堆重要的事情
and if we spend a week trying to find an office,
如果我們花上一個禮拜 找辦公室
and he and I put 20 hours into it
然後他跟我花上20
or 50 hours into it, it's a huge waste of time.
或是50個小時, 那真的很浪費時間
I thought they'd be in multiple bags
我本來想說他們會分裝
rather than one big one, but hey...
而不是裝在一起 反正...
I believe that Bitcoin will do to the banking industry
我相信比特幣對於銀行的衝擊
what email did to the postal service.
會不亞於 E-mail對郵遞服務.
It didn't make it irrelevant,
他並不是直接取代,
what it's forced the post office to do
而是強迫郵局轉型
is concentrate on their strengths
加強他的優點
and less so on their weaknesses.
並弱化他的缺點
Mike Caldwell is the creator
Mike Caldwell 是實體比特幣
of physical Bitcoins,
的發明者,
known as Casascius coins.
這些被稱做casascius硬幣.
They're often featured
這些常常出現在
in mainstream media coverage of Bitcoin.
主流媒體的比特幣報導中
They're a novelty item,
這是個新東西,
collectables that basically act
是具有收藏價值
as physical carriers for Bitcoins.
也是比特幣的傳遞媒介.
But they do something very important.
但也擔任了重要的任務,
They give Bitcoin a face.
那就是讓比特幣有了形體.
Come on in.
請進.
Sorry, the kids are sleeping,
抱歉小孩在睡覺,
so I'm just being quiet so we don't-- you know.
而小聲一點就不會--你知道的.
Each coin has its own Bitcoin address.
每個硬幣都有自己的比特幣地址.
And the private key required to spend it
以及藏在全息圖下面,
is hidden underneath the hologram.
可以花費他的私鑰
This is where you make the physical Bitcoin.
這就是你做實體幣的地方.
Yeah. It's a random smattering of things,
對啊,雖然東西看起來很亂,
but I'm pretty careful about the way I manage--
但我都有仔細保管--
You know, the--
你知道的,--
Basically, this is the credentials.
這些其實要保密.
This is the hologram and the private keys.
因為上面有全息圖跟密鑰.
I'm pretty careful about those and don't keep them here.
我通常都很小心,不會放在這邊.
I normally do them on this mirror
我通常在這個鏡子上弄
'cause that helps me get the fronts and backs right.
因為這樣我方便對準前後
There's so many things that cryptography can do for us,
加密學可以幫我們很多,
that if the world just knew,
如果全世界都認識的話,
so many social problems could be solved.
很多社會問題就能解決了.
Cryptography can bring fairness to elections.
加密技術可以給我們 公平的選舉機制.
It's too difficult for people to understand
因為實在太難懂
and someone needs to bridge the gap.
所以一般人還是需要入門的方式
Right now we're using Bitcoin to send money.
現在我們是用比特幣 在傳送金錢
But many believe it will revolutionize much more.
但很多人相信 比特幣背後的
The technology behind Bitcoin
無法作弊的
can be used to build decentralized systems
分散式技術
with rules that can't be cheated.
將可以改變很多事情
Now see, this is my wife and my space.
這個是我太太跟我用的地方.
- This is, you know-- - Awesome.
- 然後這看起來-- - 很好.
It is what it is.
就是這樣.
The more time goes by,
隨著時間過去,
the more legitimate Bitcoin gets
比特幣越來越受到接受
and the more proud I am to be associated with it.
我也很榮幸我身在其中.
Now what does your wife do?
你太太在做什麼的?
She does crafts.
她做手工藝的.
She's a lot like me.
她跟我很像.
We just sit around and make things all day.
我們可以坐下來 做一整天的東西.
It's just our obsession.
這就是我們的愛好.
No, I'm not a drug dealer. No, I'm not a criminal.
不,我既不是毒販 也不是一個罪犯
No, I'm not a terrorist.
我也不是恐怖份子
I believe in the rule of law.
我相信法律
I believe in structure that builds society.
以及我們的社會架構
I believe in families.
我也相信家庭
I believe in corporations.
也相信企業
I believe in all the essential elements
我相信一切必要的東西
that a civilized society with law and order
一個文明社會需要法律與規範
need to be able to function.
才得以運作
Focal length matters.
這些是必然的.
Cryptography is the basis
當我們相信一個東西有價值,
for us being able to implement the values we say we believe in.
加密學就是很重要的工具.
This idea will never die,
這是個永續的概念
the technology that Bitcoin brought to the forefront.
而比特幣把它帶到前面了
The genie is out of the bottle.
精靈從瓶子裡被釋放了.
Since the crash, the Bitcoin price
經過之前重挫,比特幣的價格
has been hovering around $100.
一直在100左右徘徊
Bitcoins seem to have weathered the storm,
比特幣的風暴似乎已經過去,
but there's still much controversy surrounding the currency.
但依然有許多的爭議.
The same cryptography that insures a user's privacy
保障其使用者隱私的科技
also allows it to be used anonymously.
同時也可被匿名使用
My father decided to retire
我爸有一間輸出店
and he had an old failing print shop.
但是他決定退休了.
I basically took it over
所以我就接手過來
and I converted it into an Internet place.
改成一個小網咖.
We're the only place in L.A.
我們目前是洛杉磯唯一
That supports Bitcoin right now.
接收比特幣的店家
This is my Linux system here.
這台是我的linux.
It's a system that also mines for Bitcoins.
同時也是我的礦機.
Makes about a dollar a day. I just do it for fun.
一天大概有一塊錢美金, 我只是開來好玩的.
I was really really into the Internet,
我很早就上網了,
literally in 1990, 1991, 1992,
差不多就在 1990, 1991, 1992的時候
and I had the hardest time describing
那時候你很難去跟別人
what the Internet was to people.
解釋什麼叫做Internet
I would tell people, "well, it's like this network of computers.
那時我跟其他人說
And the network of computers
"這是一個電腦的網路,
can talk with other networks of computers
裡面的電腦都可以互相溝通,
and then you could exchange information."
你就可以透過這樣交換各種資訊"
And people would have no idea what it was.
可是他們根本聽不懂
- - When people ask me what Bitcoin is
- 當別人問我比特幣是什麼的時候
I have the hardest time describing what it is.
我又很難跟別人解釋
And I'd surmise it as, "it's basically money.
我只好說 "他是一種貨幣
It's basically an anonymous PayPal.
你可以把它當作匿名的paypal
It's one of those things that you have to use
這是你先用了
before you understand.
才會知道的東西
Politically, I'm not a very big fan
其實我不太支持銀行或是
of either the banks or federal reserve,
所謂的聯邦儲備銀行,
and Bitcoin allows me to get around that.
而比特幣可以讓我規避.
One of the programs we support is a protocol called "Tor."
我們有一種程式叫做"Tor"
And basically what Tor does is it allows you to communicate
Tor可以讓你在網路上
to a website anonymously.
與一個網站匿名通訊
Tor is a program that allows you to get on the silk road.
Tor可以讓你上到"絲綢之路"
And this is silk road.
這就是"絲綢之路"
Basically, any drug you want is available.
基本上你要買什麼藥都有
There's a lot of weed. There's a lot of cocaine.
有大麻 有古柯鹼
There's a lot of ecstasy.
還有快樂丸.
But there's also unusual drugs,
也有一些不常見的,
like if you want some sort of anabolic steroid,
比如說你要一些合成類固醇,
you can type "steroid."
你只要打"類固醇"
You'll get all the different types
你就能找到各式各樣
of steroids that are available.
的各種類固醇.
Silk road itself is not selling the drugs.
"絲綢之路"本身不賣藥
This is basically a matchmaker
他基本上扮演一個
between buyer and seller.
買家跟賣家的仲介角色
Both the buyer and seller don't know each other.
但是買賣雙方均不知道對方身份
Both the buyer and seller are anonymous.
買賣雙方均為匿名.
It goes on this web of trust.
他是一種網路信賴機制.
If you want to, let's say, buy this testosterone,
比如說你要買雄激素,
you'd click on this.
那你點開這個,
He has 99.3 positive feedback
這個賣家有99.3的正評
from more than 300 transactions.
也交易過超過300次
So even though the contracts aren't enforceable by law,
雖然法律管不到這些交易
the reputation system makes it so that
但由於這個評價機制
the system works pretty well.
所以運作得依然很好
Oh, there's a fireworks section now. I didn't know that.
這邊還有一個"煙火"專賣區, 我其實不知道這是什麼
Florida I.D., 1.88 Bitcoins,
Florida身份證., (要價)1.88 個比特幣,
which is around $150, something like that.
差不多是150元的價格.
A forged auto insurance card,
假的汽車保險證,
forged passport.
假護照,
There is over 9,000 entries for drugs.
光藥物就有超過9000項商品.
That's a lot.
其實很多.
I would say there's around maybe five customers
我這邊大概有5個客人
that know about it and use it.
知道並在上這個網站
It's a very small percentage of the people that come in.
其實佔來客數非常少.
But the people who do know about it,
但是知道這個網站的人,
specifically come here to use it.
會特別跑來這裡用.
What the customers do with the computers
客人要怎麼用電腦
is pretty much their business.
基本上是他們自己的事情.
Another day in the office.
又是普通的一天啊.
You gonna do drug dealing of any sort,
你如果要做毒品交易,
silk road is the place to go.
找"絲綢之路"就對了
How many people are selling cannabis right now?
現在有多少人在賣大麻?
It looks like 2,011 people are selling cannabis.
這邊說有2011個人.
They call me Mr. Bitcoin.
他們叫我比特幣先生.
I probably been dealing drugs
我大概從17歲開始
since I was like 17.
就在賣毒品了吧
Right now I'm 26.
我現在26了
I think of it as a global thing
當我坐在電腦前
when I'm on the computer.
我認為這是全球化的事情
I'm doing business with the world.
我是在跟全世界做交易
Let's see, they have blue dream,
讓我看看, 他們有藍色夢幻,
sour diesel, pineapple Thai,
靈魂燃料, 泰國鳳梨,
purple kush, girl scout cookies. Purple pays.
紫色庫什,女童軍餅乾. 葡萄派吉.
When I first heard about it,
我一開始聽到,
I was laughing about it. It took me a week
我還根本不相信. 我花了一個禮拜的時間
to just even think about this for real.
去想這個的真實性
"I can really make money off the Internet?
"我真的可以透過網路賺錢?
Selling this type of stuff on the Internet? You sure about that?"
在網路上賣這些?你確定?"
This something I probably may buy right here.
我應該會買這個.
They have looks like some good kush.
看起來很不錯的庫什.
And some of these things only take a day to get here
有些只要花一天時間 就能送到
with no harassment from nobody
而且不會被別人騷擾
instead of just being on the streets.
比起街上交易差很多
Once you get the hang of it, it's actually kinda fun
當你會用了以後, 其實還蠻好玩的
just looking through different things.
可以看到很多不同的東西
"Mr. Bitcoin." I'm running with it.
"比特幣先生" 這是我現在的名號.
I like the name. You know what I mean?
我喜歡這個名字. 你知道嗎?
I'm not gonna lie. I get Booty off this.
我不騙你. 我還因此有不少豔遇.
I kinda like talking about this stuff with girls.
我喜歡跟女生講這些東西
Girls like that shit hot.
她們也喜歡這些新事物
"Oh, you're street, and you got a little nerd knowledge?
"喔?雖然你在街上混,但是你也會一些宅知識耶
This is great."
好厲害."
I have a lot of Bitcoins saved up already.
我現在存了不少比特幣.
My business is doing good.
現在生意也不錯.
It's a fun way of doing hustling these days.
這樣做生意挺有趣的.
The future brung a different way to hustle
未來科技讓我有了不一樣的生意
and I like it.
而且我喜歡這樣.
With so many people using Bitcoin
當越來越多人
in so many different ways,
透過各種不同方式使用比特幣
it's becoming apparent that it can't be ignored.
也就越來越不可忽視他
- Let me see your driver's license. - Oh sure.
- 請讓我看你的駕照. - 沒問題.
This stays at the desk until you leave the building.
這個會保留到你離開這棟大樓為止.
Today I'm visiting FinCEN,
今天我來採訪FinCEN
a bureau of the U.S. department of the treasury.
美國財政部的一個單位.
Despite having released guidance on virtual currencies,
雖然已經發出 虛擬貨幣的管理規範
there's still a lot of uncertainty surrounding their outlook
在他們的觀點來看
on the future of Bitcoin regulation.
未來仍有很多監管的未知數
Straight ahead and in the big fishbowl-looking--
直走,然後會遇到一個魚缸形狀--
Okay, great.
好的.
I'm not gonna say we're gonna have
我不保證今天
every answer for you today,
有辦法回答你的所有問題
but I mean...
但我的意思是...
Oh yeah.
現在是每天5到10次. 是的.
Jennifer Shasky Calvery came onboard
從去年開始擔任
as FinCEN's director last year.
fincen的主任.
During her career, she spent 15 years
在她職涯中,他花了15年
at the department of justice
在美國司法部
where she specialized in fighting money laundering
專門研究洗錢與
and organized crime.
組織犯罪防制.
Virtual currencies have been on my radar
在我來這裡之前
for a while, even prior to coming
我已經注意虛擬貨幣
to this position, because of,
有一段時間了, 因為,
unfortunately, the abuse of some of them.
裡面存在一些濫用的問題.
Bitcoin, on the other hand,
那在我到這裡之前
is one that really didn't come on my radar
則沒那麼注意
probably until I arrived at FinCEN.
比特幣的動向
Depending on who you speak to,
我們之前發出的通告
the issuance of our guidance was
對於比特幣來說,可能是好的發展
either the best thing that ever happened to Bitcoin
也可能是最壞的發展
or the worst thing that ever happened to Bitcoin.
要看你說話的對象而定
Some accusing us of trying to kill Bitcoin
有人指控我們正在消滅比特幣
and others saying that it somehow legitimized it.
也有人覺得這是某種監管方式
Of course, neither of those things I think is probably true.
我覺得這兩種說法都是事實
And certainly neither of those things was our intent.
而也都不是我們的目的
One of the clear lines is that if you're a consumer
顯而可見的是,如果你只是一個
who's using Bitcoins to buy goods and services,
使用比特幣買東西跟服務的人
the guidance doesn't pertain to you.
這個監管令並不適用於你
We're focused more on the places where we think
我們主要關注的目標是
we have risks to the U.S. financial system
我們認為會對美國金融系統有威脅的地方
from money laundering and terrorist financing.
像是洗錢或是資助恐怖份子等
And I think that might be kind of--
我想這大概也是--
A lot of the Bitcoin community has a little bit of a fear
比特幣社群這幾年害怕的地方
that Bitcoin may be characterized
當一些人濫用之後
in a way so as to tie it to some bad actor ruining it for everyone,
就把比特幣貼上這樣的想法
when a lot of people that are interested in Bitcoin,
當很多人對比特幣有興趣,
including myself, see it as just this technology that we don't--
包含我,都是因為這樣的技術,
Really don't wanna see it falling
而我們當然不想他
into the wrong categorization
被劃入一種錯誤的想法中
with all the potential that's there.
尤其當潛力還很大時
Sure. So that innovation around Bitcoin
當然,比特幣跟虛擬經濟
and the virtual economy
的發明
is really one of the more interesting aspects,
是一種重要的發展方向
I think, of this story-- The idea that
我想最重要的方向
it can be used to potentially serve
是他有潛力成為
the unbanked out there,
在銀行業無法服務的地區
just to provide some really new services
提供給群眾
that are convenient for consumers.
成為一種新的服務方式
The flip side of it though
反過來講
is that to be a part of the financial system--
如果你要成為金融系統的一員,
The U.S. financial system, the global financial system--
無論是美國金融系統 還是世界金融系統
Also comes with some responsibilities.
也需要承擔一些責任.
And those responsibilities include
那些責任包含
not allowing your institution to be used
不要讓你的系統
by criminals and by terrorists.
被罪犯或恐怖份子使用
There's always been a concern
一直以來都有人擔憂
that the government might try to stamp out Bitcoin.
政府將要封殺比特幣
But perhaps they see the risk of being left behind.
但他們也看到被時代拋棄的風險.
In may 2013, the biggest gathering to-date
2013年五月，盛大的比特幣聚會 在舊金山展開
of Bitcoin enthusiasts and entrepreneurs
與企業家
happened in San Jose, California.
到加州Jan Hose
We're at Bitcoin 2013.
我們現在在比特幣2013
It's the inaugural conference of the Bitcoin foundation.
這裡是比特幣基金會成立大會
Roger Ver: Bitcoin is worldwide and the vast majority of people
比特幣是全球性的貨幣
haven't even heard of Bitcoin yet.
但是大多數人都還未曾聽過
It's more powerful than every computer
他的運算能力已經超過了
on the top-500 list combined.
世界前500強電腦運算能力的總和
It's an awfully big world,
這是一個大世界
an awful lot of things could happen.
會發生很多不好的事情
Really, we've been on a roller-coaster ride
我們已經經歷不少大起大落
and I expect, at least for the next few years,
不過我覺得在接下來這幾年
we're gonna remain on a roller-coaster ride.
我們還會經歷一些糟糕的事情
I happen to enjoy roller coasters.
我還蠻喜歡大起大落的雲霄飛車
I think they're fun.
因為很好玩
Just a few weeks earlier
幾個禮拜以前
Cameron and Tyler Winklevoss,
因為對Facebook投資而著名,
known for their involvement in Facebook,
的 Cameron 與 Tyler winklevos,
announce that they own a 1% stake
表示他們擁有目前現存
of all Bitcoins in existence.
百分之一的比特幣
Worth around $11 million.
價值約一千一百萬美金
- How's it going? How are you? - Nice to meet you.
- 怎樣了？你好嗎？ - 真高興看到你
They also made a $1.5 million investment
他們也另外對Charlie的Bitinstant公司
in Charlie's company, Bitlnstant.
投資了一千五百萬
We started looking seriously at it
去年夏天開始
at the end of last summer
我們開始認真看這件事情
and started purchasing around that time.
那時候也才開始認真投入
I think a light bulb just went off and we said, "wow.
我當初的點子忽然冷靜，想到，哇
The implication of this could be enormous.
這真的是影響深遠
If everyone in the world could have a Bitcoin address,
如果世界上每個人都有一個比特幣地址
everyone in the world could be banked fairly quickly.
那差不多每個人都是自己的銀行了
And when you consider that,
當你這樣想
it's a very powerful idea.
會發現這是個大點子
And Bitcoin can make that happen.
而比特幣將讓他發生
We're going all over the world.
我們將到全世界去
We're going to the U.K.
我們要去英國
We're going to Australia.
我們要去澳洲
We're going to-- We're already in Russia.
我們也要去--- 我們已經去了俄羅斯了
We're going to South America.
我們要去南美
We're already in Brazil now.
而我們去過巴西了
You can buy Bitcoin at any of our locations.
你可以在我們佈點的任一地方 買到比特幣
It's fun to think that Satoshi might be here too.
如果satoshi在這邊的話應該會很好玩
I always wonder if somebody is--
我總是在猜會不會誰是--
If someone here somewhere is...
如果在這裡某個人是...
Yes. I was planning-- -... Standing in the corner going--
- 其實我有想說-- - ...站在角落然後--
What would he do?
他會做什麼？
What talks would he be attending, you know?
他會參加什麼講座？
Trace Mayer: We're seeing the Bitcoin players in the Market
我們現在看到很多的 比特幣玩家
meeting with the venture capitalists
跟創投者們互動
and they're all beginning to posture
他們都似乎蠢蠢欲動
and that's very exciting,
這是非常好的
because it means that
這表示說我們
there's gonna be a lot more
接下來會有更多關於
infrastructure built out,
比特幣的創造出現
and lot more money flowing into the space,
而且有更多的錢投入
and it's really gonna be a big bull Market for Bitcoin.
看來會對比特幣造成牛市
One of the companies best known for making
在亞特蘭大的BitPay 以協助商家
Bitcoin accessible for commerce is Atlanta-based BitPay.
導入比特幣支付而著名
They are pioneers in Bitcoin
他們是比特幣的先驅者
and provide a service that enables merchants
提供一個給商家收比特幣的管道
to accept Bitcoin payments
卻不需要去面對
without dealing with its complexities.
其中太複雜的難題
We've grown about a factor of 10
我們從今年年初開始
since the beginning of the year.
大概增長了10倍的規模
We were doing about half a million dollars a month...
我們一開始 每個月處理約50萬元美金
- Yeah. - ...Around the turn of the year,
- 對. - ...到了今年,
and now we're doing about $5 million a month.
每個月大概五百萬
This is people using Bitcoins to buy real goods and services.
這些人就是用比特幣買東西.
They're not day trading. They're not exchanging.
不只是交易. 也不只是兌換而已.
They're actually buying things.
他們真的在買東西.
I'm confident that Bitcoin is the most important invention
我真的覺得比特幣 是Internet發明之後
in the entire history of the world since the Internet.
的最偉大的發明
Roger Ver is an investor
Roger ver是比特幣產業
in several early Bitcoin companies,
的早期投資者
including BitPay.
其中包含BitPay
His passion and enthusiasm
他對比特幣的熱情與投入
has earned him the nickname "Bitcoin Jesus."
使他贏得了「比特幣上帝」的綽號
It is going to change everything.
他將會改變一切.
And all of you here in this room
在這裡的所有人
you're at the very very forefront of that.
你們剛好踏入了最早的一步.
Roger lives in Tokyo
Roger住在東京
but travels the earth, spreading the good word of Bitcoin.
但經常到處旅遊 就是為了宣傳比特幣
The last couple of days we've been setting up
最近這幾天 我們正在試著
a business per day to accept Bitcoin here in the bay area.
在灣區這裡每天說服一個店加收取比特幣
Today's business is going to be
那今天輪到這個
this Super Kyo-Po Korean supermarket.
kyo-po韓國超市
So for you-- you accept credit cards right now?
所以你-- 現在在收信用卡嗎？
- Right. - The credit card companies are charging you 2% or 3%?
-對. - 每次收2到3%手續費?
- For Bitcoin, you can do the same thing,
- 對. - 用比特幣的話,
but they'll only charge you 1%
他們只收你 1%
and you'll still get dollars in your bank account.
而你也會在你的銀行帳戶收到錢
If you want, you can choose to split
如果你要的話 也可以選擇
some of the payments that you receive
把收到的金額部分留著存比特幣
into Bitcoins and then some into dollars
而部分換成現金
in whatever ratio you want, so you can keep 99% in dollars
不管你比例要多少, 你可以99%現金
and 1% in Bitcoin or 99% in Bitcoin and 1% in dollars.
1%比特幣 或是 99%比特幣跟1%現金.
-  Okay. - However you want. You can decide that.
- 了解. - 你自己可以決定比例
Roger is describing the service
Roger正在講的
provided by BitPay.
就是Bitpay的服務
They take the volatility of Bitcoin's price
他們處理了比特幣匯率變動的方法
out of the equation for merchants
就是將商家收到的比特幣
by immediately converting Bitcoins to dollars
在交易當下
at the time of sale.
即時轉換成美金
So right now we have it set to 100% dollars,
我們現在設定100%轉成現金
so anybody that pays here with Bitcoin,
所以這邊付比特幣的交易
they'll deposit the money into your bank account
你隔天就會在銀行帳戶看到入帳
the very next day with only a 1% fee.
只收你1%手續費
And I guarantee you over the next couple of weeks
而且我保證 在接下來幾個禮拜
you'll have lots of computer nerds
你會遇到一些
that love Bitcoins will be coming in here
愛用比特幣的科技人
specifically to shop at your supermarket,
來到你們這間超市消費
so that they can pay with Bitcoin.
就只是因為能用比特幣
The credit card companies, just for processing the payment,
那些信用卡公司 就只是處理帳務
they take anywhere from...
就收從1.5%到3%不等
1.5% to over 3%
的手續費
and then on certain cards
在一些特定的卡片
there's even a per-transaction fee,
還要收處理費,
like 20¢ per transaction
每次大概20美分
plus the percentage of the transaction.
還要加上交易手續費.
...$11,000, $12,000 a month
他們每個月
on the average that they just take right out of our account.
可以從你帳戶拿走1萬1或1萬2不等
I honestly think that
我真的認為
there's a really good chance
有很大的機會
that Bitcoins will be more than $1,000
比特幣會在今年底漲到超過1000美金
by the end of the year, because everybody who hears about--
因為大家都知道了
"wait, I can send money to and from anyone I want?"
"我可以隨時隨地轉帳給任何人"
It's impossible for anyone to freeze your account,
沒有人可以凍結你的帳戶
it's impossible for anyone to block you from sending or receiving these Bitcoins.
也沒有人可以阻止你接收或轉帳比特幣
...Euros, so you can see
...歐元, 所以可以看到
all these different currency exchanges around the world
全世界各地的交易所
that exchange to and from Bitcoins.
他們都在交易比特幣
You can see there's maybe between 50 and 100 exchanges now.
你看現在差不多有接近100間
When I first heard about Bitcoin and started telling everybody about it,
我剛開始接觸比特幣,在跟大家宣傳的時候
if you looked at that same page, there were less than 10.
在這一頁上只有不到10間（交易所）
And there's no central office that they could raid or anything like that?
而且沒有一個可以搜查的中央辦公室之類的？
There's no central-- It's amazing.
-沒有一個中心. 真神奇.
There's no central office,
他沒有中央辦公室
there's no central place they could go to
也沒有一個中心,這些人可以去
and say, "take Steve's Bitcoins,"
然後說"把Steve的錢拿走"
or, "give Steve's Bitcoins to Kevin." Do this or do that.
或是"把"Steve的錢給Kevin"之類的事情
So who's the owner of Bitcoins?
所以誰是比特幣的所有者？
- Everybody that owns Bitcoins? - Yeah yeah.
- 就是持有比特幣的人? - 對啊.
Just like who's the owner of gold? It's whoever owns some gold.
就像誰是黃金的所有者? 就是持有黃金的人.
Short of shutting down the entire Internet
除了關閉整個世界的網路
in the entire world, there's no way to stop Bitcoin.
不然沒有方法禁止比特幣
And hit "request payment."
按下 "請求付款"
And that's the Q.R. Code for your Bitcoin address.
那就是你的付款地址的QRcode
So I'm gonna scan that...
所以我掃描...
So now I have your Bitcoin address on my phone.
那我現在有你的地址了
I think this is $2,
這個應該是2塊錢
so I'm going to send you $2
所以我要轉給你價值2塊錢
worth of Bitcoins.
的比特幣
There it is. You just received that many Bitcoins
就是這樣,你剛剛收到了
from me, directly with no fee
這些比特幣,還沒有手續費
and if you hit the little green square
如果你按下綠色按鈕
it'll show you the equivalent amount in U.S. dollars.
他會顯示美元匯率給你看
So you just received $2 worth of Bitcoins
所以你剛剛收到了2美元的比特幣
directly from my phone to your phone.
從我的手機轉到到你的手機
And you can send money just like that anywhere in the world.
你可以在全世界這樣轉帳
You could've told me your Bitcoin address
你也可以在臉書
by email or posted on Facebook
或是email或是twitter或其他地方
or Twitter or anywhere.
貼上你的付款地址.
So I could print this and have it at the register.
所以我可以把這個印出來貼在 收銀機
Yeah. Yup, and you can check right on your phone
對,而且每次收款後
any time that you received the payment.
你可以直接在手機上看到
Okay. Thank you, Steve.
-  Ok,謝謝你, Steve.
-  All right. Thanks. - Thank you for the tea.
-  好的,謝謝. - 謝謝你的茶.
One of the newest standouts in the Bitcoin space
比特幣產業的另一顆新星
is a San Francisco company named Coinbase.
是舊金山的Coinbase公司
They operate a digital wallet service
他們提供數位錢包服務
that makes it simple to buy, use and accept Bitcoin.
讓使用者得以簡單的 收付與接受比特幣
I would not be surprised at all
如果Google, square, PayPal在這一兩年內
if Google, square, PayPal-- Everybody--
開始接受比特幣付款的話
Is looking at adding Bitcoin in one or two years.
我完全不會感到驚訝
By then we need to have 50 million wallets.
到時候我們會需要 5000萬個數位錢包
If we can make this easy to use,
如果我們可以簡化他
it's gonna be huge.
將會發展得很快
Fred Ehrsam: My involvement in Bitcoin is not politically motivated.
我對比特幣的投入並不是 政治動機
- Yeah, dude. -  People are realizing large capital gains.
- 太好了,朋友. 大家開始注意到有資本投入.
When professional investors enter the realm,
當專業投資人進來時,
the stakes definitely change.
就開始改變局勢
We raised $5 million from union square ventures.
我們從union square ventures 獲得了500萬的投資
Fred Wilson led the round there.
Fred Wilson是那邊的老闆
I think Bitcoin is still
我認為比特幣還沒有
actually a little bit under the radar.
進入大家的視野裡
I think it's moved past the stage where people dismiss it,
大家已經過了拒絕使用的階段
but I don't think that it's totally
但我不認為他已經進入了
gone mainstream either.
世界主流
I think we're in that middle stage right now.
我覺得現在在中間的階段
At the end of the conference,
在大會的尾聲
Jered from Tradehill threw a party
tradehill的jered開了個派對
to celebrate how far things had come.
來慶祝目前比特幣的進展
You guys are hot right now.
- 你們現在很紅耶.
- Yup. - Congratulations on the raise.
- 對啊. - 恭喜你們的高昇
- Thank you. - It's good money, man.
- 謝謝. - 那筆錢真的很好.
- Swell do. - Yeah.
- 會有回報的. - 對啊.
I mean-- - hopefully it's an advancement for the community.
- 我是說-- - 希望對社群是個大推動
I am completely pro-compliance.
我是完全想要守法的
I think if you don't want to attach your identity to this,
我覺得如果你不願意提供身分
- just can't work with you. - Yeah, so I thought I just need to--
那你不能用這個(服務)
I mean the libertarian side of me is like, "ehh. Yeah, whatever,"
我在自由主義的那一面覺得 "隨便他們怎麼搞都行"
but like, from a business perspective,
但是在生意人的觀點看
if people don't play by the rules,
如果你不照ˋ著制度走
- you're not gonna last. - Yeah, I completely agree.
-你不會玩得很久. -對,沒錯
- You're gonna just shut down or you're gonna go to jail. - Yeah.
你可能會被迫關門,或是你被關. -對啊
Noticeably absent from the conference
另一件大會中令人注意的事情是
were representatives of Bitcoin's
比特幣業界最大的交易商
biggest exchange, Mt. Gox.
mt. Gox並沒有出現
Just days earlier the department of homeland security
就在幾天前,美國國土安全局
seized more than $5 million from their U.S. accounts.
從他們的美國帳戶中扣押了500萬美金.
The seizure warrant stated that Mt. Gox had failed
扣押令指出mt. Gox
to register as a money transmitter,
並沒有為金流業務註冊
putting them in violation of the new FinCEN guidelines.
此舉違反了Fincen頒佈的規章
I'm traveling to Tokyo to meet Mark Karpeles,
我旅行到東京與Mark Karpeles見面
Mt. Gox's reclusive C.E.O.
他是 mt. Gox的CEO
No Bitcoins on here.
這裡沒有比特幣
Not yet.
還沒
That will make this completely unnecessary.
(比特幣)就不需要這樣了
But for now it seems kind of primitive
這種方式看起來很原始
that we're exchanging paper for paper.
用紙鈔換紙鈔
-  And losing. - And losing value.
- 還有損失. - 損失價值.
Someone's taking a cut. Someone's taking a little percent.
某個人拿一點 那個人也拿一點
Mark and his business partner Gonzague
Mark跟他的合夥人gonzague
are French but they operate Mt. Gox from offices in Japan.
是法國人 但他們在日本營運 mt. Gox
Originally Mt. Gox was an exchange for trading cards
mt. Gox一開始是魔法風雲會的
- used in a game called - The Gathering."
手遊卡的交易中心
M.T.G.O.X. Stood for
M.T.G.O.X.是
ic: The Gathering online exchange."
Magic The gathering online exchange 的簡稱
In 2011 Mark's company Tibanne
2011年Mark的公司tibanne
bought Mt. Gox, and his focus has been Bitcoin ever since.
收購mt. gox，從此就以比特幣當作經營目標
One of the conditions of my visit
我來訪的其中一個目的
is to refrain from any discussion
就是討論美國國土局
about the D.H.S. Seizure,
在進行中的調查裡
due to the ongoing investigation.
扣押了mt. gox資產的事情
We've arrived at Mt. Gox.
我們到mt. gox了
This is Mt. Gox right here.
這就是mt. gox
There's no big sign or anything, no-- no--
沒有大招牌或什麼其他東西
It doesn't look like a crazy commercial establishment.
看起來不像一個新興產業的地方
Despite their legal problems
雖然有法律問題
Mt. Gox still handles more volume than any other exchange
mt. gox依然是交易量最大的交易平台
and is processing around
每天處理大約
$6 million worth of Bitcoin trades every day.
價值600萬美金的比特幣交易
We had, last year, an average of 10,000 new customers a month.
我們去年每個月大概有1萬個新客戶
January, it was 20,000.
一月的時候2萬
Then 30,000, 60,000,
後來3萬,6萬
150,000.
15萬
With what's going on, we go down,
就這樣發展 我們遇到問題
but we are reaching 100,000 new customers
但增加了10萬個客戶
- for may. - That's amazing.
- 在五月的時候. - 真厲害.
- In a month? - In a month.
- 一個月內? - 就一個月.
- Wow. - So it was like this...
- 哇. - 就像這樣...
Zip, bup!
漲,跌
But still, after what happened
但其實 在發生那些事情後
I thought that a lot of people will go away
我想說很多人會離開（這個平台）
or don't create a new account.
或不願意再開戶
But still, 100,000 new customers
但是, 我們增加了10萬個客戶耶
it's... wow.
真是,哇
And here we've got the office.
這裡是我們的辦公室
Mt. Gox employs 18 people
Mt. gox 有18名員工
not only is Mark the C.E.O.,
Mark不但是CEO
he's also the C.F.O., the lead developer
他同時也是CFO,
and performs all technical operations to keep the exchange running.
又是交易平台上, 負責技術與效能的主管
- C++. -  C++.
- C++.
Is that your main-- Is that your main
那是你的主要語言？
-  programming language? - No.
- 你的主要開發語言？ - 不是.
I've got a lot of main programming languages.
我會一堆程式語言
Yeah? What's your favorite programming language?
喔？那你最喜歡用哪一種？
Really depend on what I need to do.
其實要看你要做什麼
I create a good something really quick
如果我要很快的寫一個東西
and I don't care about performance,
但是又不用在乎他的效能
I use P.H.P.
我就會用PHP
If I care a little bit about performance,
如果我有點在意效能
I will use c++ with Q.T. Available.
我就會用 c++ 與q.T.
And if I care a lot about performance, I will use Axum.
如果我很在意效能 我就會用axum.
When we go in, cameras down first,
我們進去的時候, 攝影機先關掉
- until we get to your servers and then back up. - Exactly.
- 等到了主機那邊再開機. - 沒錯.
Okay.
OK
Getting ready to go into the Mt. Gox data center location.
我們準備進入Mt. gox的機房
Okay, cameras down.
OK,攝影機關機
We were allowed to snap a few photographs
我們被允許拍幾張照片
If Mt. Gox's new trading engine
如果Mt. gox的新交易系統
can really support 100 million orders per second,
每秒可以處理數以億計的交易量
it should be able to scale with the demands of professional traders.
那應該可以符合專業交易者的需求
But with complex legal problems and increasing competition,
但隨著法律問題與競爭者的接近
Mark's attention is pulled in many directions.
Mark需要面對很多的挑戰.
Do you work seven days a week, typically?
-你平常每週工作七天？
- Yup. - It seems that you do
- 對. - 看來你做的都是
the majority of all the heavy lifting.
一些粗重的工作啊
- Literally. - Yeah.
- 自由主義啊. - 沒錯.
You need to remove your shoes in the entrance.
你進來之前要先脫鞋
Mark is a talented man
Mark是一個住在大城市裡
in one of the world's biggest cities...
的天才
But maybe he should stick to computer keyboards.
但也許他應該繼續在電腦鍵盤上努力
Okay, I messed it up.
看來我搞砸了.
- Awesome. -  Yay.
- 太棒了. -  耶.
Yeah.
耶
Erik Voorhees. We are here in northern New Hampshire
我現在在北南新罕布夏州的
for the porcupine freedom festival.
松樹自由節活動.
And this is an event put on each year
這是自由美洲計畫
by the free state project.
每年一度的活動
Basically it's just a bunch of crazy anarcho-capitalists,
基本上就是一群瘋狂的安那其資本家
libertarian types in the woods,
還有自由主義者
with freedom and families.
大家在森林裡一起相聚的活動
Pretty much all of the vendors accept Bitcoin.
幾乎所有的攤位都收比特幣
It tastes much better when bought with Bitcoin.
用比特幣買感覺更好喝
Thanks, guys.
謝啦
Soups, salads and smoothies.
湯,沙拉,還有奶昔.
I would say one-third of our sales
我們有差不多三分之一的交易
have been in Bitcoin.
是用比特幣的
It's 20 bucks. So you're gonna pay in Bitcoin?
總共20元, 你要用比特幣付款嗎？
- Uh, yeah. - All right.
- 是的. - 沒問題.
Last year was our first year accepting it
去年我們開始收比特幣
we did maybe 18 transactions, 20 transactions at the most.
大概有18-20筆交易
And now we're up to close to 120.
現在我們有接近120筆
This community is really one of the largest groups
這裡大概是美國
of people in the U.S., I think,
最大的其中一群真正接受比特幣
that is truly adopting Bitcoin and using it as a currency,
並把他當作貨幣使用的人
because of what it stands for and because of what it enables.
因為它的意義與它的功用使然.
The world is seriously changing now
這個世界真的正在改變
and it is changing in a very interesting,
它正在用一個非常獨特
very radical, decentralized,
非常激進,而且分散的方式
and, in my opinion, positive direction.
而我認為是正面的方向.
Shoot. Here it is.
看,在這裡
"Price breaks the all-time high."
"價格來到新高"
Vitalik is only 19 years old,
Vitalik目前僅19歲,
but he has a profound understanding
但他對比特幣卻
of the complexities of Bitcoin
了解得非常透徹
and a gift for explaining them.
而且知道如何解釋
As lead writer for "Bitcoin magazine,"
因擔任"比特幣雜誌"的主要寫手
he's been traveling the world, covering Bitcoin for the past year.
他去年到處旅行 並撰寫比特幣的文章
I'm a big fan of the decentralization concept, in principle.
我對分散式概念的東西都很有興趣
You know, have lots-- Lots of different societies
現在有很多不同的社群
operating according to whatever people's own beliefs are.
信仰著不同的信念
Bitcoin has unique properties
比特幣的獨特
that no other system in the world has had before.
是這個世界從沒有過的
It really seems like the only practical way forward.
看起來是進步的唯一方式.
As you move away from cash
當你不用現金
into your debit cards and your credit cards,
而改用信用卡和簽帳卡時
you essentially are giving up
某種程度你已經
a certain degree of your privacy
放棄了你的某些隱私
without even really knowing it.
你還甚至不知道
It's important to understand that Bitcoin is not
重點是,比特幣並不會自動的,
automatically, perfectly anonymous.
匿名,或是自動無法追蹤
But what it does is it enables you to be anonymous if you wish to.
但如果你需要他可以匿名
Erik Voorhees is the founder and part owner
Erik voorhees是著名的比特幣
of a hugely popular Bitcoin gambling site
賭博網站Satoshi Dice
called Satoshi Dice.
的創始人與合夥人
Satoshi Dice is the first of a new breed
Satoshi dice是首個使用比特幣
of provably fair betting games
的公平公正
that use Bitcoin.
線上賭博網站.
Since all bets are public,
由於公開了所有紀錄,
anyone can verify the odds and payouts.
每個人都可以驗證機率與付款
At its peak, Satoshi Dice was responsible
在尖峰時期,Satoshi Dice網站
for more Bitcoin transactions
的比特幣交易數量
than all other uses of Bitcoin combined.
超過了其他交易行為的總和
It played an important role in Bitcoin's development
該網站在比特幣的發展有著重要地位
as one of the first applications
因為它是首個測試
to really test what the Bitcoin network could handle.
比特幣網路負載交易量的系統
Recently Erik moved his entire operations out of the U.S.
最近,Erik把全部業務從美國遷出
And into Panama.
搬到巴拿馬
He started a company called Coinapult
並開了一間新公司-coinapult
that lets you send Bitcoin via s.M.S. And email.
讓你可以用簡訊或email寄送比特幣
I think most people,
我認為多數人
at least in America,
至少美國人
believe that when they put $1,000 into their bank,
都相信如果他們在銀行 存入1000元
the bank is holding $1,000 in its vault for them.
那銀行也會在保險箱中 為他們保管著1000元
And they don't realize that 99% of all the dollars are digital.
但他們不知道其實99%被電子化了
The fact that we have these tokens called paper cash
其實我們手上的紙鈔
is the exception to the rule.
反而是個例外
People see the cash and they think that that's what the money is,
大家看到紙鈔認為這就是金錢
but it's all digital and it's been that way for decades.
但其實幾十年來都已經電子化了
You guys moved your business to Panama.
你們把公司搬到巴拿馬
What was the primary driver in that?
是什麼原因讓你們這樣做？
If you're a U.S. company,
如果你是一間美國公司
you have to follow the arcane U.S. regulations
就算你的顧客從世界各地而來
for all of your customers around the world.
你還是要遵守美國的法律
So if you do business with some rural farmer in Africa,
如果你跟南美洲某個農夫做生意,
you're gonna need to get his social security number,
你要他的社會安全號碼,
all this information
你還要他提供 所有政府認為
that Washington tells you is important.
重要的資料
We did not want to have to apply
我們不想連南非的顧客
the U.S. financial regulatory scheme
都必須要遵守這套
to customers in sub-Saharan Africa.
美國的金融法律規範
I don't think the developed world's
我認為已開發國家
gonna be where Bitcoin really takes off, long-term,
並不會是比特幣真正長期發展蓬勃的地方
because our banking system's worked decently well.
因為我們的銀行系統已經太好了
Many people around the world
但在世界有些地方的人
don't have any bank accounts whatsoever.
根本沒有銀行帳戶
Ultimately, those are the types of people
到最後那些人才是
who will find the most value out of Bitcoin.
真正知道比特幣價值的人
One month later Erik announced
一個月後 Erik宣布
he had sold Satoshi dice to an anonymous investor.
他將Satoshi Dice賣給了一位匿名買家
The price?
售出價格？
126,315 Bitcoins,
126,315 比特幣
worth around $11.5 million.
現值差不多1150萬美金
Most of the new offices in this city are in this condition,
這個城市的新辦公室差不多都是這樣
all still what's called "gray."
我們就稱之為"灰色狀態"吧.
Not ready, no Internet, no electricity-- nothing.
還沒好,沒網路,沒電力,什麼都沒有
But we actually got one that was finished,
不過我們找到一個完工的
so we moved in and we are super excited about it.
所以我們很興奮可以搬來這邊
You can see all the skyscrapers
你可以看到很多銀行跟其他
of new banks and everything getting built up here.
的辦公大樓都在這裡
This is the financial center for central America.
這裡是中美洲的金融中心
So it was fitting that we establish ourselves here as well.
在這裡開展業務也很合適.
Still setting up the office.
我們還在整理辦公室
We've been here for two weeks.
我們已經來兩個星期了
We're getting walls put in.
牆壁裝好了
We've got furniture.
也有加遽了
This is the brains of the operation.
這位是我們營運的大腦
-  This is Mr. Ira. - Howdy.
- 這位是Ira先生. - 你好.
He can program anything, and you can see all these books he's reading.
他幾乎可以寫所有程式 你看他這裡讀的書,
What have we got here? We've got "cryptanalysis."
有什麼書？ 有"加密分析"
We've got "everyday cryptography,"
還有 "每日加密學"
"introduction to mathematical cryptography."
"數字加密學入門"
I read all of these, of course, when I was much younger,
這些我都看過, 當然是在我年輕的時候啦,
but Ira's trying to catch up with me.
看來Ira想要追上我
The Bitcoin phenomenon is trying
比特幣現象其實是把
to take control of money away
受到國家控制的金錢
from the state and return it to individuals.
的控制權交還給個人
It's trying to separate money and state
把金錢與國家分開
in the same way and for the same reasons
的重要性,不亞於當初
that it was important to separate church and state.
把國家與宗教分開的重要性
There's a wonderful quote from one of the Rothschilds--
Rothschilds家族曾說過一句名言--
"give me control of a nation's money
"讓我控制國家貨幣
and I care not who makes its laws."
我就不在乎誰控制法律"
So I'm trying to play my part in that narrative.
所以我想要做好我的工作.
Outside of the United States,
美國以外的地方
billions of people don't have access
有數以百萬計的人無法享有
to basic banking services.
基本的銀行服務
Bitcoin can level the playing field
比特幣可以減少差距
and help bring developing nations
讓發展中國家的人
into the global economy.
也可以進入全球經濟體
Cheers, cheers.
乾杯.
Eventually people are going to use a currency
到最後大家一定會用一個
that is as free as the Internet
如同網路般自由的貨幣
because people will seek out freedom wherever they can.
因為人類總是竭盡所能尋求自由
And just as the government can't stop the Internet
就像政府不能關閉網路
and the freedom of speech, it can't stop Bitcoin and the freedom of money.
,言論自由,也不能關掉這個自由的比特幣
So we're just gonna have to see how hard they try to do it.
所以我們將會看到他們如何去嘗試
It's scary but it's exciting,
聽起來很可怕 也很振奮
because at the other end freedom typically wins.
因為自由通常都會勝利
We just have see how long it takes to get there.
我們只是要看需要多久時間
As summer rolled on,
隨著夏天來臨,
the Bitcoin industry continued to flourish.
比特幣業界持續火速發展
It's hard to remember the days where I was
幾乎快要忘記那些在我地下室
running this thing out of my basement
只有一兩個人在弄
and with one or two people.
這個公司的日子
Bitlnstant was just a domain name.
Bitinstant當時只是個網址而已.
Charlie and Bitlnstant
Charlie與他的bitinstant公司
moved into their new offices
搬進了新的辦公室
I always wonder if Satoshi knew
我總想要知道
that he was gonna build something that would foster
如果Satoshi知道說
companies like this,
大家都不知道他
where we're actually like a company with jobs
但是那些寫在紙上的(比特幣基礎)
based on something that someone we don't know wrote a paper on.
卻孕育了我們這些公司.
It's kind of creepy if you think about it.
想起來好像有點恐怖.
I wonder if he's watching us right now or something.
我在想他是不是都有在觀察我們
In San Francisco,
在舊金山這裡
Jered and Tradehill had moved
jered和tradehill也搬到了
into their new space as well.
新的辦公室
It sounds funny. It's not a $100-million Market anymore.
聽起來很好玩, 他已經不是一個億元市場
It's grown beyond that.
已經超過那個價值了
More professional people are in the space
越來越多專業人士來這裡
and they're expecting to deal with other professionals.
他們想要跟其他專業人士有所交集
But just as things were ramping up,
不過正當事情蓬勃發展時,
regulators started taking a closer look at Bitcoin.
監管機構更加關注著比特幣.
Some bad news for Bitcoin, or is it?
我們有一些比特幣的壞消息,是嗎?
Its days of glory could be ending.
輝煌的日子可能要結束了
At least two dozen companies
最少有二十幾間公司
have been subpoenaed by New York's
遭到紐約金融服務部門
department of financial services.
的傳喚
Can't be a good thing.
看起來不是好消息
Bitlnstant, BitPay, Coinbase
Bitinstant, bitpay, coinbase
and Winklevoss capital were all issued subpoenas.
與winklevoss投資都在傳喚名單內
We want to make sure that as this enterprise grows
我們只是要確認
and if it does become a place where
在這些公司運作的地方
a lot of people are engaging in financial transactions
其中的金融交易活動
that we have sufficient protections in place.
我們能提供足夠的保護.
With increased pressure in banking compliance issues,
迫於與銀行間的法規問題,
Bitlnstant was forced to suspend services.
bitinstant被迫暫停其業務
Jered faced similar battles.
Jered也遇到的類似的問題
Due to a lack of regulation,
由於無法令監管
many banks decided to cut ties with Bitcoin companies.
許多銀行決定不與比特幣公司往來業務
Without a U.S. bank account
沒了美國的戶頭
Tradehill can't operate,
tradehill無法繼續運作
and Jered was forced to pull the plug.
Jered只好被迫關門
Regulation typically evolves
管理法規通常
much more slowly than innovation.
都比創新來得慢上許多
And regulations cannot keep pace
而且監管機構無法跟上
with the pace of innovation.
創新發展的腳步
Explaining Bitcoin to a bank
跟銀行解釋比特幣
feels like explaining Amazon. Com
就像是跟Barnes & noble(傳統書局)
to Barnes & noble.
解釋什麼是Amazon.com
Until lawmakers catch up,
在立法腳步趕上之前
startups like Tradehill and Bitlnstant
tradehill與bitinstant這類的公司
are left out on a limb.
都無路可走
Banks do not want to bank Bitcoin companies.
銀行不想跟比特幣公司往來
When you have regulation, you can comply with it.
當你有法條時,他們會照著走
When you don't have any regulation, they're not exactly sure.
當你沒有任何規章,他們就不知道怎麼做
And if the banks aren't sure, they just default to "no."
他們不知道怎麼做,通常都會說"不"
New regulation takes at least one year to develop
新法案通常需要一年的時間
propose and adopt.
來研究、提案與推行
And in many cases,
而很多的例子表示
it can take much longer than that.
可能會花上更多的時間
I won't let this go.
我不會放棄
I will fight till the end for Bitcoin.
我會努力到比特幣的末日
Whether I have to work on the street or sell lemonade,
不管我要在街上工作或是賣飲料
Bitcoin's gonna succeed one way or another
比特幣會成功的,我一定
and I'm gonna be a part of it.
要在其中
Over the past several months
在過去幾個月裡
the Bitcoin mining landscape has changed significantly
比特幣礦業版圖變化很多
When I started,
當我加入時,
Bitcoin mining was a hobby for geeks.
挖礦只是電腦人的樂趣.
Now it's big business.
現在則是大事業.
In order to continue mining
為了能繼續挖礦
and continue playing in the game
繼續參與其中
and be competitive and be profitable,
而且還要有競爭力及獲利
I would have to spend
那我就得花上
hundreds of thousands of dollars on gear.
數十萬美金去買(挖礦)設備
The 18 miners I ordered from Avalon
我從avalon買的18台礦機
never arrived.
遲遲沒到貨
And the units from butterfly labs
butterfly labs出的礦機
took over a year to ship.
則花了一年才送到
By the time I got them,
我收到它們的時候
Bitcoin mining was so competitive,
挖礦已經太過競爭,
that I would never be able to mine back
我已經不可能把我當初
all the coins I used to buy them.
買礦機的費用挖礦挖回來
See that computer? That computer makes Bitcoins.
你看到那台電腦嗎？ 那台就是產生比特幣的
And this is all the other computers that are making Bitcoins too,
那些都是在產生比特幣的電腦
and it goes straight up in a line up in the air.
你看這條線往上衝很高
And that's 'cause there's a lot people
那是因為很多人
that are making Bitcoins with computers like that.
都在用像這樣的電腦在挖礦
As my new units are arriving,
當我的新礦機到貨後
I'm selling them for Bitcoins
我直接把他們賣掉換比特幣
to try to recoup what I can.
多少補償一點損失
If you don't mind grabbing those other cables,
你能不能拿著那些電線
- I'm not coming back up. -  Okay.
- 因為我不會再回來了. -  Ok.
I'm taking a pretty big hit...
我的損失頗大
But overall the mining experience
但總體來說, 整個挖礦的歷程
has still been worth it.
還蠻值得的
My mining days may be over,
我挖礦的日子可能結束了,
but I'm still very involved with Bitcoin.
但我依然熱心投入在比特幣上.
With Bitcoin, it's a money system where
比特幣是一個依靠在
it's backed by math. It's back by the laws of mathematics
數學,應該說數學規範
and by the rules of the protocol.
以及它本身的協定
I keep thinking that there's gotta be an easier way
我一直在想應該有更
to just set up a secondary protocol
簡單的第二套方法
to trade private keys.
來交易這些密匙
Every time I log on, I see another dot on China
每次我登入系統 看到中國又有另外一個點(使用者)
and I'm like, this is why right now the price has gone up.
我就會想說, 這就是為什麼又回到150元的原因
The price is nearing 150 again.
價格又來到接近150,
Many attribute it to the explosion
對此貢獻良多的
of Bitcoin's popularity in China.
是在中國的比特幣社群
What's happened recently is Chinese people
原因是越來越多的中國人
have really come and adopted Bitcoin.
真正的開始導入比特幣
As a culture, as a nation
因為國家文化因素
Chinese people are keen to learn about
中國人常常去學習
things that are on the Internet,
網路有關的東西
things that involve math and science.
以及跟數學科學相關的東西
We think that China can really contribute in this space
我們認為中國可以對
and help bring Bitcoin to the mainstream.
將比特幣推入主流有重要貢獻
Germany's another part of the world
德國是世界的另一個
where Bitcoin has found a home.
比特幣生根之處
It's starting to get normal if one person a day
現在開始看到一天
comes in and buys a coffee with Bitcoins.
有一個客人用比特幣買咖啡
People are looking for a new way of paying--
大家在找一個新的付款方式
Not through banks, not with Euros,
不通過銀行,或歐元
not with dollars. Something new.
或美金. 而是新的東西.
The German ministry of finance
德國財政部
even became the first governing body
也是第一個政府部門宣告
to officially classify Bitcoin as "private money."
比特幣為"私人貨幣"
I believe if we want to get
我相信如果
some justice back into our society,
我們要拿回一些社會正義
we should reduce the importance of the banks.
那我們要減少對銀行的依賴
Bitcoin is banking without banks,
比特幣是一套不需要銀行的 金融系統
so here we go.
所以我們來用吧
The FBI today shut down what it's calling
FBI今天關閉了號稱
the most sophisticated Internet site
最為複雜的地下網站
in the business of selling hard drugs,
這個網站專門賣毒品
including heroin, cocaine and LSD.
例如海洛因、古柯鹼與迷幻藥等
In the Sci-Fi section
在舊金山圖書館的
of a San Francisco public library,
科幻圖書區
undercover agents surprised a young man
臥底幹員找到了一位在
quietly working on his laptop.
筆電上工作的年輕人
They arrested a 29-year-old software engineer
他們逮捕了29歲的軟體工程師
named Ross Albrecht
Ross Albrecht
and accused him of being the mastermind
並控告他是絲綢之路網站
behind the silk road.
的主謀
People have always tied the silk road to it.
大家都把絲綢之路跟(比特幣)放在一起
Media has always tied the silk road to it,
因為媒體就是這樣(比特幣)放在一起講
as if silk road is Bitcoin, but it's not.
好像說絲綢之路等於比特幣, 當然不是.
This may be a sign that Bitcoin is growing up.
這也許是比特幣成長的一種現象吧.
It's funny. My friend just I.M.'D me and said,
這個很好笑, 我朋友剛剛丟訊息給我問說
"silk road got raided
"絲綢之路被查了
and the government seized $3.6 million in Bitcoin.
政府扣押了價值360萬的比特幣
Is there a way to invalidate Bitcoins?"
我們有辦法廢除比特幣嗎？"
I replied, "no."
我就回他, "沒辦法."
People are starting to finally realize
大家開始留意到
that Bitcoin has nothing to do with how people use it.
比特幣跟使用者沒關係
It's just money. It's like gold.
就跟金錢一樣. 就像現金.
Of course, not everyone thinks
當然, 不是所有人都認為
Bitcoin is the way of the future.
比特幣有前景
Bitcoin will not be able
比特幣如果不
to survive or thrive
納入規範的話
without becoming legitimate.
它將沒辦法發展
I don't see it
我在金融系統內
having a serious place
看不到一個可以
in our financial system.
容下它的地方
There are really good reasons
為什麼我們的
why we have central banks
央行可以發行鈔票
that have the power to put out financial fires
那是因為金融系統有
by printing money.
很好的理由這樣做
I'm worried about the technology.
我對這個技術很憂心
As Darth Vader once said,
像是達斯維達說的,
"don't put all your faith in technology."
"不要完全相信科技"
I think 10 years from now,
我覺得十年以後
we'll look back on this and just kind of chuckle
我們會嘲笑比特幣
at the Bitcoin fad.
的這個時候
"Oh yeah, I remember Bitcoin.
說"喔對,我記得比特幣
Oh yeah, I remember that."
喔對,我記得有這個東西."
It's financial freedom.
這是金融自由啊.
Come on, bro. This is the new world, bro.
來吧,這是個新世界.
Others are more optimistic.
其他人則很樂觀
I think within 10 years,
我想在10年以後
you're gonna have a lot of people using Bitcoin,
會有很多人在用比特幣
but they're not gonna realize that they're using it,
但他們可能不知道正在用它
because it's gonna be a protocol that's imbedded underneath
因為它可能會就是你今天在用的
whatever financial service they're using today.
金融系統的底層架構
And by Bitcoin being open-source
藉著比特幣的開放原始碼
it's what can allow all these different mobile wallets
可以讓各種不同的手機錢包
and all these financial technologies
和不同的金融科技
to all talk to each other,
可以互相溝通
especially around the world.
甚至是全球性的溝通
Whoever the hell Satoshi was,
不管satoshi是誰
he should go down in history as one of the greatest people
他會像不少偉大的人都被
or groups of people that ever existed.
被歷史的洪流所遺忘
This is a technology that mankind has needed
這是個人類需要的技術
for thousands of years.
幾千年來
People have been dealing with monetary shenanigans
大家都在用金錢貨幣交易
since the Roman empire clipping gold coins.
從羅馬時代的金幣就開始了
And finally people can escape it.
大家終於可以從中解脫
I'm cautious to try to predict the future.
我對未來的想法很謹慎
We don't really know.
因為我們並不知道
I tend to be a technological optimist.
我對科技是很樂觀
I see the democratization of technology
看見科技中實現民主
as being a really positive thing.
是很正面的事情
And I think that's a really powerful force
而我認為這是一個
that is really only just beginning.
剛在發展的強大力量
Not bad. Oh!
不錯嘛, 喔！
Recently, as the price has been floating around 200 again,
最近價格漲到200左右,
I have a lot of friends that have asked me,
我有些朋友就問我說
"are you gonna cash out some of your Bitcoins now?
"你要把一些比特幣換成法幣嗎?
The price is really high. You should get some dollars out of it."
現在價格很高,你應該換一些美金的"
I kind of tell 'em, "no, don't you see it?"
我都回應說, "不,你沒看到嗎？"
I've met so many interesting people
我認識一些有趣的人
and there seems to be one thing that kind of binds
他們都會把很多東西
a lot of them together, and that is that
混在一起講
they're willing to face opposition
他們都會被反對
and follow through on the ideas that they believe in.
但又回到它們認同的事情上
The people who try the crazy ideas
至於那些比較前衛的人
often fail and then everybody likes to point their fingers
通常都被眾夫所指並
and laugh and say, "that was such a stupid idea."
然後被嘲笑說, "那真是太蠢的點子了."
But once in a while it works out.
但有些時候行的通的啊
I think Bitcoin is proving to be
我認為比特幣
one of those things.
就是其中之一
The decision to bring virtual currency
將虛擬貨幣納入
within the scope of our regulatory framework
法令規範架構下
should be viewed as
的這個行為可視為
a positive development for this sector.
是一種正面的進展
I'm here to testify, because I believe
我在這裡作證,我相信
that digital currency represents
虛擬貨幣將會是這個時代
one of the most important technical
最重要的技術與經濟中
and economic innovations of our time.
最重要的發明.
We are enthusiastic about the potential
我們對於虛擬貨幣
of virtual currencies
在社會助益的潛力
and the digital economy for social good.
有著很大的信心
This latest generation of technology
我們今天在這裡討論的
which we're talking about today
新科技發展
takes things to a whole new level.
將所有事情提到了一個新的層次
There's a bit
這裡必須討論
of a shared responsibility here
一些大家的共同責任
in trying to figure out how to make this work.
還有我們要怎麼做這些事情
It is a little strange that Bitcoin--
雖然我們不知道
We don't know who the creator is
比特幣的發明者是誰
and so that often
而這就會讓我們
conjures up the idea that there's
想到說裡面會不會
some risk here that we have not--
有所風險,所以我們不...
You don't think it was Al Gore, do you?
你覺得不是Al Gore（美國前副總統） 就不行對嗎？
If you think a little broadly,
如果你想遠一點
this could, again, have huge huge implications.
其實是有很大很大的影響的
2013 was the year Bitcoin first entered the mainstream
2013是比特幣嘗試進入主流的一年
and 2014 got off to a dramatic start.
2014則遇到了想不到的發展
Just as we were wrapping things up on our film,
就在本片拍攝接近完成時,
Charlie Shrem was arrested
Charlie shrem 在阿姆斯特丹
after returning from a Bitcoin conference in Amsterdam.
參加完比特幣大會後被(美國)逮捕
He could be facing up to 30 years in prison
他可能面臨30年的牢獄之災
on charges related to his activities at Bitlnstant.
這些指控都與bitinstant有關
In J.F.K., you walk right off the plane,
在JFK機場降落以後
and you go straight to customs.
走到海關櫃臺那邊
About three agents in front of me
就有三個官員站在我前面
and then four agents behind me said,
四個站在我後面
"Mr. Shrem, please come with us."
說"Shrem先生,請跟我們過來"
They took me to an interrogating room,
他們帶我去審問室,
told me that I'm being arrested
然後說我被逮捕了
on federal crimes of money laundering,
罪名是聯邦法的洗錢罪,
running an unlicensed money transmission business
非法進行金流業務,
and failing to file suspicious-activity reports.
還有並沒向政府報告可疑(金融)行為
The indictment alleged that Charlie had sold Bitcoins
起訴書提到Charlie賣比特幣給
to a reseller that operated on the silk road.
絲綢之路的其中一個中盤商.
What sucks is the house arrest.
更遭的是居家軟禁
I have to pretty much be here all the time, every day. I can't even go outside
我幾乎隨時都只能待在這邊,也不能出門
unless I'm going to my lawyer's office, which is once or twice a week.
除非我是去律師那邊,那也是每週一兩次
I pretty much lost my freedom,
我沒了自由
lost everything that I've built over the past year.
也幾乎損失了我去年做一切
Charlie's arrest wasn't the only bad news
Charlie被捕不是這年來唯一
that rocked the community in the new year.
唯一嚇到社群的壞消息
For months there had been rumors that Mt. Gox had become insolvent.
mt. Gox破產的謠言已經謠傳了幾個月
And in February the site went offline.
二月,他們的網站關閉了
Do you still have everyone's Bitcoins?
大家的比特幣還在嗎?
I'm not touching you. I haven't touched you.
我沒有碰到你喔. 都沒碰到你耶.
The rumors turned out to be true.
結果謠言是真的.
Mt. Gox had reportedly been hacked
Mt. Gox表示系統遭到入侵
and nearly half a billion dollars worth of Bitcoin were missing.
損失了價值將近5000萬的比特幣.
Mark was forced to step down as C.E.O.
Mark被迫離開CEO的位子
And Mt. Gox went into bankruptcy.
mt. Gox則進入破產清算階段
A national magazine claims to have identified
一本全國發行的雜誌 聲稱他們已經找到
the mysterious founder of the worldwide
名聞世界的虛擬貨幣-比特幣
digital currency called Bitcoin.
的發明人
Tonight he is speaking out,
今晚他公開現身,
but he says he has
但他表示
nothing whatsoever to do with Bitcoin.
他與比特幣一點關係也沒有
Why did you create Bitcoin, sir?
你為什麼發明比特幣？
Okay.
Ok.現在不是發問時間 我要去吃免費午餐了
Man *2: Sir, can we ask you about Bitcoin?
我們能否問比特幣的問題?
- No no no no no. -  Why were you involved in Bitcoin?
- 不不不不. - 你為什麼會參與比特幣的工作?
Okay, I'm not involved in Bitcoin, okay?
Ok我跟比特幣沒關係,好嗎?
-  Who's involved in it? - Wait a minute.
-那誰有參與? -等一下.
I want a free lunch first.
我要去吃免費午餐.
I'm gonna go with this guy.
然後我要來找這個人
I want a big one. Yeah.
我要一份大份的. 太好咯.
Oh, okay. Yeah, this will be good.
喔,ok,太好了, 看起來很棒.
- Oh jeez. - We have some water.
- 喔,天啊. - 我們還有一些水.
Hey, where's yours?
嘿,那你的勒?
"Newsweek" claimed the creator of Bitcoin
"Newsweek"表示比特幣的發明人
had not used a pseudonym.
並沒有用假名
They connected the dots
他們抽絲剝繭
to a 64-year-old Japanese man
找到了一位住在洛杉磯的
living in Los Angeles...
64歲日本人
Named Dorian Prentice Satoshi Nakamoto.
全名為Dorian prentice satoshi nakamoto.
Nakamoto immediately denied the allegations
Nakamoto先生立即否認這些傳言.
and said he'd tell his story to the first reporter
並說他因為第一個記者說
who agreed to buy him lunch.
要請他吃午餐他才這樣說的
The main reason I'm here is
我願意在這裡的主因
to clear my name, that I have nothing
是要澄清一件事是說我跟比特幣
- to do with Bitcoin... - Yup.
-一點關係也沒有 -了解.
...nothing to do with developing.
...跟開發也沒關係.
I was just an engineer doing something else.
我只是一個做其他工作的工程師.
As the media frenzy escalated,
隨著媒體效應增加
"Newsweek's" claims started to unravel.
"Newsweek"的說法逐步曝光
Holes in the story led many to believe
其報導的漏洞讓越來越多人相信
it was nothing more than sensational journalism.
這只是一個新聞炒作手法
There was no conclusive evidence
沒有決定性證據證明
tying Dorian to Bitcoin.
Dorian跟比特幣的關係
Amidst the uncertainty,
為了消滅謠言,
on that same day...
同一天,在Satoshi很久沒更新 的個人網頁上
on Satoshi's long-dormant profile page which read...
出現了一條動態： "我不是Dorian Nakamoto"
Maybe we'll never know who created Bitcoin...
說不定我們永遠找不到發明人...
But the truth is
但事實上
it doesn't really matter.
其實根本不重要.
Bitcoin belongs to everyone.
Bitcoin是屬於每個人的.
And the future is ours to build.
而我們可以締造歷史
Put $100,000 on Market orders right now.
趕快買1000塊.
- Why? - Let's do it. Let's do it. Come on.
- 為什麼? - 做就對了. 快點快點
- Come on. - Why? What's gonna happen?
- 快點. - 怎麼了?會怎樣啊?
Buy 100k worth of Bitcoins right now.
現在買10萬塊的比特幣.
- Why? - Do it.
- 什麼? - 外點啦.
- I don't wanna do it.
- 我不要. - 快點.
You owe me $100,000. Do it.
你欠我10萬塊啦.
I'll send you $100,000 in Bitcoins.
我會轉給你10萬美金的比特幣.
No, you buy it. But 100k right now.
不,你現在要買. 現在買10萬塊.
Dude, I can't. I need the floating Gox for volume.
不行啦,我要看gox有沒有那個量啦.
Closing bell for Satoshi square!
satosh交易所要關門啦!
All right, does this look right?
這看起來對嗎?
1-n-p-w? Yup.
1-n-p-w? 對嗎.
Yup, okay.
對, OK.
And I owe you 0.2?
我欠你0.2?
- Uh... 0.18. - 0.18.
- 應該是 0.18. - 0.18.
This is for Bitcoin t-shirt.
這是比特幣t-shirt的錢.
I got 'em. A pleasure, sir.
我收到了. 這是我的榮幸,先生.
Great doing business with you.
很高興跟你做生意
- Gonna wear your shirt proudly. - Do it.
- 我會趕快穿你的Tshirt - 快吧.
That's one thing that's interesting about Bitcoin.
比特幣有一點很有趣
It's like, how do you declare losses?
比如說你怎麼說你有(財產)交易?
You point to two transactions that happened on the Internet
你在網路上找到兩個交易
and you tell the I.R.S. That you owned that?
然後跟國稅局說那是你的交易？
"Oh, I used to own that and I lost the private key."
"喔,之前是我的但是我的密匙被偷了"?
And then if you really do lose it,
但如果你真的損失
how do you write it off for taxes?
你怎麼在稅金裡面扣除？
Oh, that's gonna be interesting.
還蠻有趣的說.
We love Bitcoin.
我們愛比特幣.
Okay, guys, we're gonna play a special version of hopscotch
Ok,我們要來玩一個特別的跳房子
called "Bitcoin blockchain hopscotch."
這個叫做"比特鍊房子"
Oh, you lost all your Bitcoins!
阿,你的比特幣都不見了！
Who is Satoshi Nakamoto?
誰是 satoshi nakamoto?
I'd... rather not tell you,
我...不告訴你
- but yeah. -  Oh, do you know?
- 就這樣 - 所以你知道？
Uh, maybe not, maybe.
可能吧,也可能不知道
Oh.
喔
You know, I have a Bitcoin and a half myself now.
你知道嗎？我把我一半奉獻給比特幣了
Which I think probably in 10 years
大概會在10年內發生吧
When you think about it hard enough
當你想得深入點
on a global scale, this is a net gain for humanity.
會發現這是全球人類的共同特質